Good evening.
Good evening and Hoya Saxa.
Um
I love that call and response so much.
good evening. My name is Mo Ellethy. I
am executive director of the Institute
of Politics and Public Service at the
McCourt School
and thank you uh so much for um joining
us this evening.
Um this is the third time the Senator
has come to GU Politics.
And the first time was almost 10 years
ago to the day, almost to the day. One
of our very first big events when we
launched the Institute.
Um
A big theme of this, our 10th
anniversary year,
is focusing on the future of public
service.
Over the past 10 years since we
launched, we have seen
how this era of disruption,
economic disruption, social, cultural
disruption, technological disruption,
disruption of our information ecosystem,
and political disruption, has impacted
the world, has impacted the very notion
of public service.
As we think about the next decade,
and we think and we ask ourselves
questions about what does the future
of public service look like?
It's really, really hard to have this
conversation without thinking about the
role that artificial intelligence will
play
in all of those
uh all of those areas.
And so, I'm excited for this
conversation tonight.
The way this is going to work
is once they come out for about the next
hour plus, hour 15 minutes or so,
um we're going to engage in this
conversation. The Senator and the
Professor are going to first speak
amongst themselves.
And then uh when you see me come back up
here, that means we're ready for you
guys to join in the conversation.
There's going to be two standing mics,
one in the center aisle, one in the
balcony. So, when you see me come up
these stairs, that's your cue to start
lining up. And they uh have graciously
agreed to take your questions for the
remainder of the program.
Um
so, get ready. It's going to be
fascinating. And what I'm going to do
now is uh per our custom, introduce a
student, Helena Monseveiz, first-year uh
graduate student at the McCourt School
who is going to introduce our two
featured guests. Helena.
[Applause]
Thank you, Mo.
My name is Helena Monseveiz. I'm a
first-year Master of Science in Data
Science student for Public Policy at the
McCourt School of Public Policy.
This semester, I've had the privilege of
spending time in the GU Politics Living
Room as a member of Senator Laphonza
Butler's student strategy team.
In her discussion group, we've spent the
last 8 weeks exploring the implications
of artificial intelligence on the future
of work and the labor movement.
Our conversations this semester reflect
a growing national dialogue on AI and
its impact on work, which brings us to
today's event. It is an honor to speak
today on behalf of our school and the
incredible academic community.
We are excited to introduce today's
conversation, AI, the promise and the
peril, with Nobel Laureate Dr. Geoffrey
Hinton and US Senator Bernie Sanders.
Dr. Geoffrey Hinton received his PhD in
artificial intelligence from Edinburgh
in 1978.
He did post-doctoral work at the
University of California, San Diego and
spent 5 years as a faculty member in the
computer science department at Carnegie
Mellon University.
He then moved to the Department of
Computer Science at the University of
Toronto, where he is now a professor
emeritus.
From 2013 to 2023, he worked half-time
for Google, where he became vice
president and engineering fellow.
Dr. Hinton's research group in Toronto
made major breakthroughs in deep
learning that revolutionized speech
recognition and object classification.
Last year, he was awarded the Nobel
Prize in Physics.
Senator Bernie Sanders is the senior
Senator from Vermont, serving his fourth
term in the United States Senate after
winning re-election in 2024.
His previous 16 years in the House of
Representatives make him the
longest-serving independent member of
Congress in American history.
He is the ranking member on the Senate
Health, Education, Labor, and Pensions
Committee.
Following their
Following their conversation, Dr. Hinton
and Senator Sanders will be taking
questions from students
moderated by GU Politics Executive
Director Mo Ellethy.
Remember to join the our conversation on
social media by tagging us at GU
Politics. Now, please join me in
welcoming Dr. Geoffrey Hinton and
Senator Bernie Sanders.
[Applause]
Bernie.
All right.
It's on.
It's on. Okay.
Um first of all, let me thank all of you
for coming out. This is a wonderful
turnout.
Uh let me thank Georgetown for
sponsoring
the event and mostly let me thank Dr.
Hinton,
uh one of the world's leading
authorities on AI,
for being with us in DC today. Dr.
Hinton, thanks so much for coming.
[Applause]
[Music]
Uh the reason I invited Dr. Hinton
uh to DC
is that in my view,
uh AI and robotics
are going to have a very profound,
transformative impact
on our country and the entire world.
But,
despite that reality,
we are not hearing the kind of
discussion we need in Congress,
uh in the media,
and within American society
about what this consequential change is
about
and how we address it. So, that's what
tonight is about. We don't have all of
the answers. I certainly don't.
But, this is an an issue This is an
issue that is in going to impact every
one of your lives
and we need to be thinking about it big
time. So, we don't have a whole lot of
time this evening and there's a ton of
stuff
uh that we've got to cover. So, with
that, uh let me just start off by asking
uh Dr. Hinton uh a leading uh question.
And that is
uh I have heard Dr. Hinton
uh from folks all over the country who
say, "You know what? AI, yeah, you're
right. It's going to displace jobs. It's
going to create jobs. But, that's the
way the world has always been. We had
gone from agriculture to industry. We've
gone from industry to tech to uh
information. What's the big deal?"
So, what is the big deal? Is this
different than other types of
technological revolutions?
Yes, this is very different because the
people who lose their jobs won't have
other jobs to go to. Uh if AI gets as
smart as people or smarter,
any job they might do can be done by AI.
So, consider, for example, people who
work in call centers. They're poorly
trained, poorly paid, and AI is going to
be able to do their job better. They
often don't know the answer to the
question you ask, like why you got this
funny bill. Um AI will do better at
things like that. It'll be much cheaper,
and what are they going to do?
All right.
Uh the reality is, I think many people
know,
is that some of the very wealthiest
people in the world, uh Elon Musk,
um
Jeff Bezos, Mark Zuckerberg, Larry
Ellison, all the
multi-multi-billionaires
are investing hundreds and hundreds of
billions of dollars
into AI and robotics.
Are these people staying up nights
worrying about working-class people and
low-income people? Is that why they're
doing this investment?
They should be, but I don't think they
are.
And
I think many of them haven't really
absorbed Keynes, that if the workers
don't get paid, there's nobody to buy
their products.
And they haven't really thought through
the massive social disruption we'll get
if we get very high unemployment.
Um
Mr. Musk says said last month that AI
and robots
will replace all jobs.
Working will be optional.
Bill Gates, also involved in AI,
predicted that humans quote quote won't
be needed for most things, end quote.
Uh Dario Amodei, the CEO of Anthropic,
warned that AI could lead to the loss of
half of all entry-level white-collar
jobs.
What is your thought about
short-term and long-term impact
of AI and robotics on our economy? Are
these guys right?
I think they probably are right. Um
it may not be immediate. So, you often
see articles saying, "Oh, AI is not
going to replace the jobs. AI fails at
lots of things." It's true. AI currently
does fail at some things. What you have
to remember is we're in the very early
stages. This is a new technology.
It's getting better very fast. It's
getting better exponentially.
And trying to predict the future of it
is going to be very difficult. It's a
bit like when you drive in fog, you can
see clearly for 100 yards and at 200
yards you can see nothing. Well, we can
see clearly for a year or two, but 10
years out we have no idea what's going
to happen. But it seems very likely to a
large number of people that we will get
massive unemployment caused by AI. And
if you ask, "Where are these guys going
to get the roughly trillion dollars
they're investing in data centers and
chips?"
Um
really, you can get subscription fees,
but one of the main sources of money is
going to be by selling people AI that
will do the work of workers much
cheaper.
And so, these guys are really betting on
AI replacing a lot of workers.
Um as you just mentioned, no one can
predict what the long-term impact of AI
is.
But I think I read somewhere that you
suggested that as AI develops, and it's
developing very rapidly, we can almost
compare AI to the human brain like we
can compare the human brain today to a
frog's brain.
And I know very smart frogs, but
is that a
fair metaphor here? Um it's reasonable.
So, at present um the human brain
actually has more connections in it than
the big AI is all in the strengths of
connections
between simulated artificial neurons,
and they learn by changing those
connection strengths, and they have
about a trillion of those.
Um maybe two trillion in the biggest
ones, but often like only a mere 100
billion.
Um
the human brain has about 100 trillion.
So, we've actually got more connections
than they have at present. Um on the
other hand they get much more experience
than us. So, the big AI systems are
trained on trillions of words. Now, you
couldn't read trillions of words because
you only live for two billion seconds.
Actually, fortunately for Bernie and me,
it's about a little little more than two
billion seconds. Um
two billion seconds is about 64 years.
Um
So, we have very little experience and a
huge number of connections. They have a
huge amount of experience and not as
many connections as us. But even though
they've got less connections, so less
ability to store knowledge in these
connection strengths, they know
thousands of times more than us already.
If you take GPT-5 or Gemini 2.5 or
Claude 3.5 or whatever, um they can give
they can answer any question you can ask
them at the level of a not very good
expert. Sometimes they'll just make it
up, and experts sometimes just make it
up, too. Um
so, they know thousands of times more
than a person using only about 1% of the
connections. Um so, they're not quite
like us.
But they're already much more
knowledgeable than us, and they're
already very good at reasoning in
limited domains like mathematics. Um
Almost all the experts believe that it's
inevitable that if we don't blow
ourselves up or have massive pandemics
or something like that,
um they're going to get smarter than us,
and nobody knows what's going to happen
then. And we really shouldn't do that
until we can figure out whether people
can coexist with them, and people don't
know how.
In a in a practical sense, and I know
this is a a tough question,
how does AI in 10 years look in the
world?
How is my life different because of AI?
You talked about the incredible speed in
which they can give us answers.
Um
but
what does it mean in terms of our daily
lives?
Yeah, so predicting the future is a bit
like driving very fast down the freeway
while looking through the rearview
mirror.
Um you only have historical data.
Um
predicting the future in 10 years is
very very difficult.
So, the best way to see that is to look
back 10 years.
So, if you were to take people like me
who really believe in this neural
network approach to AI,
and you were to ask us 10 or 15 years
ago where we would be in 10 or 15 years,
um
we would have said it's very unlikely
we'll have a system that can you can
talk to in any natural language and
it'll answer any question you ask it at
the level of not very good expert. We
would have confidently predicted that
that was 30 to 50 years out. It wasn't
going to happen in 10 years. Well, it
has happened. And I think that means
that we can fairly confidently bet that
whatever we have in 10 years, it'll be
not what we expected.
I know that's a that's a sort of
politician's answer, and you'd expect
that from Bernie, but not from me. But
um
that I think that's the best I can do.
We don't know what's going to happen in
10 years, and that means we ought to be
cautious.
Uh
let me switch gear a little bit into an
area that gets me
very nervous because
it speaks to who we are as human beings
and how we relate to each other. I get
nervous
when I read that there are a whole lot
of people,
uh especially younger people, who are
now relying on AI for companionship. And
I gather there's products now that you
can wear around your neck and chat with
and go hiking with and date with and all
that stuff.
Uh if people grow up with their primary
companionship and their relationships
being AI and not other human beings,
what does that mean for us, for humanity
in general?
So, let me
emphasize what Bernie said. There's a
very good AI safety research team in
Britain that was set up after Bletchley
Park. After Bletchley Park, the UK
government didn't actually impose any
safety regulations cuz they said it
would interfere with innovation.
So, the tech people got to them. Um but
they did set up a very good safety team
funded with about 100 million pounds.
It's probably the best safety team in
the world. And they did an experiment
where they got people to use a chatbot
for I think a few weeks. And then they
said, "Okay, the experiment's over.
Would you like to say goodbye to the
chatbot?"
And almost everybody wanted to say
goodbye to the chatbot.
So, they weren't treating this as just a
tool. They were treating it like you
treat another being.
Um and that's a real problem. So, we've
evolved to deal with other people. Um we
haven't evolved to deal with some alien
beings that we're creating. Um again, we
don't know what's going to happen, but
it's worrying.
Well, I I
would say that it's more than worrying.
You know, we are
who we are because we are moms and dads,
and we have friends,
and that's kind of
what makes us human beings.
And if our primary relationships are
with
uh chatbot's
creations,
it seems to me that has a profound
impact on humanity. Does it not?
>> I completely agree. Um we we just don't
know what that impact is going to be.
All right, let me
move briefly to another subject.
Um
teachers,
maybe here at Georgetown as well, uh
worry that
uh students are using AI rather than
doing the critical thinking they need uh
to get the answers that they're
searching for.
Uh should we worry that AI will have a
negative impact on critical thinking
among young people?
So, there's an analogy people sometimes
use, which is pocket calculators. Years
ago when pocket calculators came in,
people said, "This is terrible. The kids
won't learn their multiplication
tables."
And I think if I asked you quickly to
say what 11 * 12 is, most of you won't
know. Um cuz you have pocket
calculators. Um people like me and
Bernie used to know. Um
I don't think it's a big deal for pocket
calculators. You don't need to know what
11 * 12 is cuz your cell phone will tell
you. Um
so, I actually think that's got some
relevance to this. I think what we
should think of is a person using a
pocket calculator um is the new system,
just as a person using an AI is the new
system. Now, a person using an AI can
still do critical thinking, um or they
can try and dump everything on the AI,
and that's terrible. They won't learn to
think. But I think we should not try and
sort of exclude AIs as assistants, cuz
that's the future. Um what we have to
what universities have to um encourage
is people to use these AIs well.
I maybe when we have questions and
answers, some of the students might want
to
uh relate to us your views on how AI AI
has impacted uh your educational uh
experience.
There's another issue out there that
also I think doesn't get a whole lot of
attention,
and that is uh the impact of AI
on foreign policy and wars.
Uh it is quite likely uh people like
Musk talk about millions and millions of
robots
being developed, and certainly um
nations around the world will use some
of these robots for military purposes.
Is it possible we will have armies of
robots?
And if elected officials or government
heads don't have to worry about human
casualties, what impact do you think
that might have on issues of war and
peace and foreign policy?
So, you're all too young, but if you do
some research on the web or ask a
chatbot, they'll tell you that in the
'60s there was a group called Country
Joe and the Fish, and they had a
wonderful song which had a line in it,
"Be the first one on your block to have
your boy come home in a box." This was
about Vietnam.
And if you ask, "Why don't rich
countries invade poor countries all the
time?" It's cuz they don't want their
boys coming home in a box. That's the
main political pressure against doing
it.
If you have an army of drones or
uh humanoid robots,
um
then rich countries can invade poor
countries, and the poor countries'
people may die, but the rich countries'
people won't die. Um it removes one of
the main reasons why that doesn't happen
all the time. Um of course, that
wouldn't happen if you had liberal
democratic rich countries, but as soon
as you have authoritarian countries,
they're going to invade other countries
if they can get away with it.
Um Putin would be very happy if there
weren't any dead Russians, there were
just dead Russian robots. And in the
states, the military industrial complex
would think that was great cuz there
wouldn't be any political blowback, and
the robots would be expensive.
Um so, I think it will remove one of the
main barriers to rich powerful countries
just invading little countries like
Grenada.
Um
let me get to
maybe
the issue that worries people
more than anything else, although
there's a lot to be worried about
everything we've been talking about.
And that is, and you've touched on it
already,
uh the possibility and
uh of AI
uh being more intelligent than human
beings
and essentially discarding human being
control.
Uh in the past, that was seen to be
science fiction, you know. I don't know
if any of the young people here saw the
movie 2001
where HAL, the computer, says basically,
"Sorry, uh no longer taking orders from
you."
Uh
in your judgment, is that a issue of
real concern? And what do you see as the
likelihood of that happening?
And what do we do about it?
So, when I was at Google in the
beginning of 2023,
um
back then, a lot of people, particularly
people, particularly linguists, for
example, said these AI language models
aren't really smart, they're just
statistics. Um
less people say that now. But they also
said this idea of them getting smarter
than us is just crazy, we don't need to
worry about it. That's just science
fiction.
And the main reason I went public in May
of 2023 was to say, "No, it's not
science fiction, it's going to happen."
Nearly all the AI real AI experts who
understand how it works believe that
they're going to get smarter than us.
And
we don't know how we're going to coexist
with them. But let me tell you several
reasons why it's problematic when they
get smarter than us.
Um there'll be AI agents who can do
things.
And if you want to make an AI agent, you
have to give it the ability to create
subgoals. So, if you want to If, for
example, if you want to get to Europe,
you have a subgoal to get to an airport,
and you can focus on that without
worrying about what you do in Europe.
That's a subgoal.
Now, AI agents will develop various
obvious subgoals once they've got the
ability to create subgoals. One is to
stay in existence cuz obviously they're
smart, right? They figure out they can't
achieve the goals we've given them, the
things they'd like to achieve for us, if
they don't exist. So, they'll develop
the subgoal of staying in existence, and
we've seen that already. We've seen AIs
that want to keep existing and will
actually try and deceive people who are
trying to turn them off. They will try
and exfiltrate their weights to other
systems so they stay in existence on
other systems.
Um
so, that's one subgoal. Another subgoal
is
they will want more control.
So, my belief about a lot of politicians
is that um they start off wanting to
achieve good things for people,
and pretty soon they realize to do that
they need more control, and then they
end up focusing on getting more and more
control. Um the AIs will do the same.
They will need to get a lot of control
so they can achieve the things we asked
them to achieve.
So, now you've got things that want to
stay in existence, they want to get
control,
and at that point you ask, "Well, maybe
we can just turn them off when they get
like that."
And the answer is you can't. Suppose
there was someone who wanted to turn
them off,
and suppose the AI could talk to that
person.
The AI by that point will be much more
persuasive than a person. Already, AIs
are about as persuasive as a person in
an argument. They'll be much more
persuasive than a person. So, they'll be
able to convince the person who's going
to turn them off not to do it, that it
would be a terrible terrible mistake to
do that.
And if you want an example of So, all
they need to be able to do is talk,
and then they can control the world. And
if you want an example of that, if you
want to invade the capital, which is not
far from here, um all you need to be
able to do is talk to people, and you
can get them to do it. You don't have to
go there yourself.
Um
okay.
given the fact we have discussed the
possibility of massive economic
dislocation,
uh we have talked about what AI can mean
to mental
health. We've talked about AI
perhaps radically transforming
issues of war and peace and foreign
policy.
Uh given all of these extraordinary
concerns,
why do you think there has not been more
discussion about these issues?
Um
I think one reason is cuz people don't
really understand what's happening. So,
I see my mission is to educate people
about what's happening and about how AI
works. Very few people at present
understand how it actually works.
If you want to understand how it
actually works, I did a podcast with a
very good interviewer. This is
self-advertisement, but I you're like
>> As opposed to me, right? Okay. Yeah,
you're like one of those.
A very good interviewer who extracted
from me a very good explanation of how
these neural nets actually work. And the
interviewer was Jon Stewart, who's a
hero of mine. Yeah. Um you should look
at that because that'll tell you how
they actually work, roughly speaking, in
terms that a non-expert can understand,
no equations.
Um
So, let let me Sorry, I got distracted
by my self-promotion.
Um
all right, let me
ask you this, and this, you know, is
you're a scientist, not a politician,
but
given all that we've talked about,
what should I be doing? What should the
Congress be doing?
I hesitate to say what the president
should be doing.
Not particularly relevant for this
discussion, but uh
what what should a sane government be
doing? Okay, so there's
So, there's some very simple things that
should definitely be done. They won't
answer all these problems, but even
those aren't being done properly. Um the
first thing is, if you're going to
release one of these big chatbots, you
ought to do a lot of safety tests on it,
and you ought to be required by your
government to report what safety tests
you did and what the results were.
And as time goes by and we get more
experience, we can add to those safety
tests.
>> Let me uh let me interrupt you. What do
you mean by safety nets? What What What
should
a rational government be doing? So, you
take a chatbot,
and you say, "Can I figure out how to
trick it into telling me how to make a
homemade bomb?"
And the answer is you can. So, these
chatbots, because they've been trained
on everything on the web that's
available, um they know how to make
nasty viruses. They know how to make
homemade bombs.
And after they've been trained, if you
were to just ask them that question and
you didn't do any further training, they
would tell you.
Um you then do further training where
people try and get them to say how to
make a bomb and then tell them, "Don't
do that. Don't answer that question."
Um that's called human reinforcement
learning,
um where the people ask some questions
and say, "That's a bad answer." Or
"That's a good answer."
Um it's very easy to overcome that, or
relatively easy to overcome that. And
not nearly enough testing has been done
on how to overcome that. So, there was a
very good bill a very sensible bill,
not very strict at all, proposed in
California, 1047, that got through both
houses and was vetoed by Gavin Newsom,
um strangely. Um
that just said you have to test them and
you have to tell the government the
results of the tests, and if you don't,
you can be sued civilly by the attorney
general. Even that failed. Um
so, that's just the minimum. There's
another area where there has to be
legislation, which is to do with these
things telling you how to create nasty
viruses.
Um that's probably the most urgent
threat. These things know how to create
viruses, and they can tell you how to
create viruses. Um
and they've got a sort of thin veneer
telling them not to tell you.
We need
a lot of legislation about they it must
not be possible
to get them to tell you how to create
nasty viruses. Also,
um during the Biden administration,
they realized that
if I can get the DNA sequence for a
nasty virus,
um I can send it off to the cloud, and
they will send it back in a test tube.
So, I don't actually need a wet lab. I
just send it to the cloud, and I get
this nasty virus in a test tube.
And at least they should check whether
this has a sequence for example the
spike protein of COVID. If it's got that
sequence in, maybe they shouldn't make
it.
It turns out most of the companies don't
check. Some of them do, but most of them
don't.
The Biden White House would have loved
to have legislation that said that
anybody who synthesizes these sequences
on the web has to do serious checks for
whether they're synthesizing a nasty
virus.
Uh they figured out though that there
was no point even proposing legislation
cuz the Republicans wouldn't give Biden
a win.
Their their calculation was um the
Republicans would rather Biden not get a
win than protect us from lethal viruses.
Um
right now,
um the other side of this is if a virus
does get out there, you'd like to have
good response to it.
Um we've got someone who had a worm in
his brain um getting rid of the research
on how to respond to it.
I Let me
go back to a concern that I have which
is
in many ways above and beyond the whole
discussion of AI.
Uh we are living uh in a moment in
American history
where we have more income and wealth
inequality than we've ever had.
You got one guy, Mr. Musk, owning more
wealth for example than the bottom 52%
of American households.
You have more concentration of ownership
than we've ever had.
What does it mean? These guys are not
dummies, and if they are investing
many, many hundreds of billions of
dollars in these technologies,
yes, I think we can assume they're doing
it for the money.
But what does it mean for our society
and the world when so few people have so
much power? How does that impact
Will in fact government be able to
regulate these guys or will they they be
in fact regulating government with their
wealth and power?
So, I think the US has a problem which I
put down to the Supreme Court and
judgments they've made that you can just
buy politicians. Not Bernie, but the
other ones.
Cuz Bernie gets his money from ordinary
people. Um
and there's no limit to how much you can
contribute to politicians by these sort
of
super PACs that pretend to be
independent.
Um
that means the rich can just buy the
political system. I remember when I
first got to the States as a post-doc
in um
1978,
there was a US government organization
um that protected consumers
um that said that used car dealers
should be required to tell you about a
fault in the car if they had used that
fault in the car to buy it cheap from
the previous owner.
Now, the used car dealers of America
didn't like that law,
and they paid every senator
um $10,000.
100 senators, that's just a million
dollars, and the Senate voted against
it. Um
that just totally shocked me that you
could buy the Senate for a million
dollars.
Um
so, I think
our main problem is that the rich have
much too much power and pay much too
little in taxes.
Um I just want to make one comment about
taxes.
Um
it's it's a kind of a joke. When I moved
to Canada, I I moved to Canada, then I
moved to Britain, then I came back to
Canada.
And um and I must use the mic for this.
Um
so, my next door neighbor was a
politician,
and he said, "Why did you come back to
Canada?"
And I said, "Cuz taxes are higher here."
And he said, "Um yes, taxes are too
high, and my government our government
has reduced them three times already,
and we're going to reduce them again."
And I said, "No, I said because taxes
are higher here."
And he said, "Yes, I agree they're too
high."
He could not comprehend the idea that
high taxes are good.
Um all of the research that led to this
revolution in AI was funded by
university grants to universities. It
was funded from taxpayer money.
Almost all of Silicon Valley came out of
federal grants to Stanford and Berkeley
and places like that.
Um
somehow the very rich have um people
like Murdoch have won the battle
to say that taxes are bad. Taxes are
good.
Um this is like greed is good. Greed
isn't good. Taxes are good. Um taxes are
what funds everything.
Without taxes, we wouldn't have all the
advanced technology we've had cuz nearly
all that technology comes out of things
funded by um taxes in the first place.
Um so, I think I've had my little say
now.
Okay.
All right. I have exhausted my list of
questions.
So, now if we can
hear from the students, that would be
great.
Now that we are sufficiently terrified,
here's what I'm going to ask.
Guys, let's let's
We're going to move to the questions as
quickly as possible. Here's how this is
going to work.
We've got the two mics.
One in the center aisle here, one in the
center aisle in the balcony.
When I point to you, you're up.
Please tell us who you are, where you're
from, what you're studying,
and then please frame your question in
the form of a question.
All right. We good?
Let's start in the balcony.
Oh, hold on.
Hold that mic a little bit closer. Is it
on? Yeah. Good.
All right. Let's
let's
Number six, please. Okay. Now we're
good, right? All right. There we go.
Thank you both so much for being here
tonight. I'm Lily Bethea. I'm a fr-
first year in the undergraduate school
of foreign service.
Um I was wondering, while I think we can
all agree that we have concerns over the
future of AI and how it threatens the
job market, I was wondering what you
believe the potential positives of the
future of AI are, and if you think that
it may potentially create new jobs in
the job market, and if so, what those
might look like.
Okay. That's a great question cuz we've
sort of left that out in this
discussion. And if it was just all these
nasty risks we've talked about, then the
rational thing to do would be just stop
developing AI now.
Um
but we can't do that. It's not like
nuclear weapons. With nuclear weapons,
they're only good for destroying things.
AI has a wonderful upside. It's going to
make health care hugely better. It's
going to make education hugely better.
We know that a private tutor allows you
to learn about twice as fast as a
classroom, and AI is going to be even
better than that. It's going to make a
very good tutor cuz cuz it's going to
see millions of kids like you and know
just what you don't understand.
Um so, that's why we're not going to
stop it. Um it's going to be wonderful
for lots of things. It's going to
predict the weather better. It's going
to um
in almost any industry where you need to
predict things, it's going to have
better predictions, and so it's going to
make the industry more efficient. Just
trivial things like how long a patient's
going to need a hospital bed for. If you
can predict that better, you can make
the hospital beds go further. You can
you can decide whether to discharge them
so another patient get that bed, or
whether that's a bad idea cuz they're
likely to come back again if you
discharge them too soon.
We it it can optimize everything and
make it more productive, and that's
great. Um but for the fact that it will
replace a lot of jobs, but I think it's
very important that um we understand
there's a huge upside to AI as well. And
in a decent society, increasing
productivity should be good. If the
wealth was shared equally between
everybody, that would be a great thing
to do.
Um in terms of creating new jobs, I
don't believe it's going to create as
many new jobs as it replaces. It'll
create jobs like prompt engineer. How do
you prompt this chatbot to get the best
out of it? Um
but I don't believe there'll be nearly
as many new jobs created as it destroys,
as it replaces.
Um
although good economists like Daron
Acemoglu um
aren't sure about this. They think maybe
it will. Um so, there's uncertainty
here.
And one thing to bear in mind when
discussing AI in the future is
everything's hugely uncertain.
Thank you. All right.
Thanks for the question. Go ahead here.
Hi. Thank you both for being here. Um my
name is Dia. I'm a senior in the
college, and I'm originally from the
Mississippi Delta, which is a rural part
of Mississippi.
So, Mississippi has signed quite a few
contracts with major companies like
Amazon and Exxon to build AI data data
centers, funneling billions of dollars
for economic development. This is more
of a policy question. How do we balance
this need for economic development,
especially in rural America, with these
energy environmental concerns of
citizens?
It's a real concern, and I think as you
know, communities all over the country
are rejecting
these data centers for a couple of
reasons.
Uh number one,
uh as often as not, their electric bills
are going to soar.
And communities in rural areas are
saying, "Why am I paying an increase
in my electricity bill in order to lose
my job?" So, they're rejecting that. And
also, as you indicate, it's not just
enormous consumption of electricity,
it's also consuming a great deal of
water.
So, there are real
uh environmental impacts associated uh
with data centers that I think
communities all over the country
are responding. And what we are seeing
is many of these very, very large
corporations are trying to bulldoze
their way through. And they're a lot
more powerful than some local city
council, you know.
So, it it is a real political issue
right now. You're seeing governors in
Virginia, for example, I think it was an
issue in the campaign.
We've got to do something about rising
electric rates because of these data
centers. So, from an environmental
perspective, which we had not discussed,
it is a very big issue. I have a comment
about that, too. They should be building
their data centers on Hudson Bay. On
Hudson Bay, you could build more
hydropower stations. There's still
untapped rivers there.
Um and the problem is you have to build
the transmission lines. But if you put a
data center next to a hydropower
station, you don't need any transmission
lines, cuz the only thing you need to
send out is information, and information
doesn't require a lot of energy to send
out. So, a natural thing to do is have a
hydro plant um
on Hudson Bay with a data center next to
it. And I had a long conversation with
Trudeau about this, and he was very
interested in that, but it never
happened.
Thank you. Okay. All right. Back up to
the balcony. Thank you very much. I'm
Juliana Valadares. I'm a faculty here
teaching at the School of Foreign
Services, a course on AI and Human
Rights in Latin America. And my question
is on the international governance,
could you share any reflections of what
would be an ideal governance model?
And if there are any limits that should
be in place, in your view,
uh including on new technologies in the
military domain, which was a topic that
you touched upon today. Thank you.
So, for a long time, I've been against
lethal autonomous weapons. That is,
weapons that decide who they should kill
or maim by themselves.
Um
the US military says there will always
be human oversight.
But to begin with, they said that
wouldn't happen. Then they said there
would always be human oversight. Um and
what that means is there'll be oversight
of the policy, but you have to make the
decisions too fast, so these things will
be deciding who to kill or maim.
And I thought it was just a clear-cut
case that we should forbid that.
Um we should have Geneva Conventions
against that, which probably wouldn't
come into place till very nasty things
had happened.
I now think it's a bit more complicated,
having talked to Eric Schmidt,
um who used to be the chairman of
Google. Um he's much more right-wing
than me, so we disagree on more or less
everything.
But um for example, he thinks
Kissinger's a good guy, and I think
Kissinger's a bad guy.
Um
I like the Rolling Stone obituary for
Kissinger. Um
so
But he made me realize, if you look at
Ukraine now,
um the Russians are using drones. Should
the Ukrainians just say, "We're not
going to use drones. We're not going to
use drones that can drop grenades on
people"?
Um it's more complicated. I mean, it
would be great if we could get
international treaties, and we have got
international treaties for chemical
weapons that have basically worked. The
Russians aren't using chemical weapons
in Ukraine. Um
a few people have broken those treaties.
Um
Saddam Hussein dropped chemical weapons
on the Kurds. There's some evidence that
Winston Churchill dropped chemical
weapons on the Kurds. It always seems to
be the Kurds that gets dropped on, but
um
but basically, they've held, and maybe
we can get international treaties like
that that'll hold for lethal autonomous
weapons. Um but I think very nasty
things will have to have to happen
first.
Uh I would just add to that that in a
world of massive inequality,
uh AI and robotics is going to be
uh just exacerbate that inequality. The
wealthy countries will be able to have
tools
uh that poor countries in a million
years won't have.
Okay, thanks for the question.
Hello. Hi, Dr. And Senator Sanders, it's
an honor to
ask you guys
questions today. I'm Chakravarthy
Gollapalli, a sophomore in the School of
Foreign Service, probably calling
Lexington, Kentucky home. And Senator
Sanders, you've been my model since
middle school, so it's an incredible
honor uh to see you and ask you a
question.
Um one thing one thing I'm studying here
at in Georgetown is global public
health, and I've been very concerned
about how, especially here in the United
States, health insurance companies could
abuse AI, in particular to deny health
care coverage to especially to those who
need it. What First of all, what do you
Could you elaborate on like abuses that
like health care insurance companies
could take could use using AI? What
should the government do to regulate
these abuses? And finally, do you
anticipate single-payer systems like NHS
NHS or Medicare for all to potentially
minimize these abuses?
Uh
to answer your question,
it is totally absurd and embarrassing
that the United States of America, the
richest country on Earth, is the only
major country not to guarantee health
care to all people as a human right.
[Music]
Well, the function of insurance
companies is not to provide health care,
it is to make a lot of money, and they
do make a lot of money. Drug companies
make an enormous amount of money.
And it it saddens me very much uh that
we have a system which everybody
recognizes is broken, it is
dysfunctional, it is enormously
complicated, and by the way,
not only are we the only major country
not to guarantee health care to all
people, we're spending twice as much per
capita as other countries. So, I think
the answer to your question is health
care is a human right. We guarantee
health care to all people,
young, old, rich, or poor.
Can I add one thing to that? Um
it is true that health care companies
can abuse AI to decide not to insure
people are going to get sick, which is
what they'd like to do. Um
however,
I think
the benefits that we're going to get
from AI in health care are a bigger
effect than that. I think we'll get huge
benefits from AI reading medical scans,
AI designing new drugs, AI being able to
take all the data about a patient, their
genome, all the tests that are done on
them, all the tests that have been done
on their relatives, and use that
information to make better diagnoses. Um
we've already seen that. Microsoft had a
system that could diagnose better than
doctors, and quite a bit better, I
think. Um so, it is true that any
powerful technology like this will be
abused by people trying to make more
money, but overall, the effect in health
care, despite that, I think will be very
positive.
Thank you so much. Thank you. Back up to
the balcony.
Uh hi, my name is Zach. I'm an
undergraduate senior, and I'm studying
human science. And I was just wondering,
have you seen the movie Wall-E?
Because I feel like what as you've been
saying with AI and all the potential
benefits, uh why does it not make sense
for us to invest all of our money, all
of our time into developing really,
really powerful super AIs, so that they
can just take care of all of our
problems, and in the future, we don't
have to like worry about things like
working in jobs?
Okay, let me answer that.
If we had a political system
that was run for the benefit of the
people, that's exactly what we should
do.
We should have very powerful AI that
does everything for us. We should be
very careful to design it so it cares
more about us than it does about itself.
I've been pushing this idea of maternal
instincts. If you look around for how
can we coexist with something smarter
than us? Well, look around to see where
does a less intelligent system thrive in
the presence of a more intelligent
system? There's only one place, and
that's a baby and a mother. The mother
cares more about the baby than she does
about herself.
Um the baby thrives. We need AI with
maternal instincts. We don't know how to
engineer that, but we're still in
charge, and we should be able to
engineer that. Um
that's part of the puzzle. We If we can
engineer that,
and we can have a political system which
aims to um help all of the people all of
the time,
um it would be great, but that's not the
political system we've got in most
places. We've got authoritarians.
Um
we have
um systems in which
some people see most of the other people
as mugs to be exploited. They're a
market. We need to deceive them into
buying our useless products, which fail
as quickly as possible so we can send
them more sell them more. Um in that
kind of system, it's very bad to develop
AI and put people out of work. But there
is the hope that we could get a system
where
it is used for the benefit of everybody.
Um a system like one big family. That's
what it should be like. Um so, it's not
just a reality question, but this is
kind of
I feel like I'm sort of 16 16 again and
thinking about how politics ought to be.
Um, it's very idealistic.
Well, I think you raise
a very important question and I think
you're saying, "Hey, this is great.
AI is going to come. You don't have to
do this job. You don't have to do that
job.
Really, really good."
Do you think that is what Mr. Musk and
Mr. Bezos have in mind?
Do you think that's why they're spending
hundreds of billions of dollars to say,
"Hey, isn't this great? We can lower the
work week. We can guarantee health care,
high-quality health care to everybody.
We can expand life expectancy. We can
solve global warming. Man, let's go do
it. That's what we want to do."
Do you think that's what these guys have
in mind?
Probably not. Probably not.
And what Dr. Hinton was saying is
exactly the issue.
Is AI or AI and robotics inherently bad?
Absolutely not.
If they are used, for example,
you already seeing some of the large
unions, like the UAW, negotiating with
the car companies and saying, "You know
what? Our productivity is going up.
We want a 32-hour workweek."
Needless to say, the companies were not
sympathetic.
But,
if we can lower the work week, if we
could do away with dangerous jobs,
improve health care for all, it's a
positive. But again, I get back to the
point that I started. Understand,
the people who are pushing this
transformable
transformable revolution are the richest
people in the world. They are not
staying up nights worrying about working
people, in my view.
They want even more wealth and they want
even more power. So, the struggle is not
whether AI is good or bad. It's who
controls it and who benefits from it.
That is really the the fundamental
issue, in my view.
All right. Thank you.
Back down here to the floor.
Hi, my name's Nick. I'm a sophomore
studying government from Florida. This
is the question for Senator Sanders.
Thank you for being here. Obviously,
we've heard a lot of talk about the AI
bubble and with that, the impending
burst that's probably going to
eventually happen with the AI bubble.
And indeed, you've heard people like Sam
Altman, the CEO of Open AI, say he
expects the government to bail out AI
industries. You know,
this is kind of a two-part question, but
firstly, you know, should a should a
bubble burst occur, how do you see
Congress uh
responding to that? And secondly, are
there similarities to the AI bubble that
you're seeing with past bubbles, like
the dot-com bubble? Do you Does it Does
it worry you that this bubble burst will
be worse than those previous ones?
>> worry me. And you know, getting back to
a point that, you know, Dr. Hinton
raised,
is, in my view, I don't want to put
words in his mouth, you have a fairly
corrupt political system.
So, when Wall Street went under, they
knew what they were doing. They knew
that they were investing in fraudulent
mortgages, et cetera.
They went under. They caused a massive
recession and they went to the
government and said, "Yeah, we made huge
amounts of money. We were crooks. We
were dishonest. Bail us out, cuz if you
don't bail us out, we're too big to
fail. We'll take down the whole economy
with us." If that was true then, I
suspect it is a lot truer right now. But
the gumption
of people who are multi-billionaires,
who are making money hand over fist,
says, "Oh, by the way, if we fail, you,
who are one of the 60% of American
people living paycheck to paycheck, we
would appreciate your bailing us out."
All right. So, that gets to another
issue. The broader issue is how we
create a government that represents
ordinary people, not just the dependent
on the campaign contributions of
billionaires.
And that is the broader political issue.
How do we create a fact a with a small
d, a democratic society where government
works to protect the interests of all
people, where AI and robotics are a
positive, not a negative for working
people. That's the issue that we've got
to address.
Thank you.
All right, thanks. Back up to the
balcony.
Um, hi. I'm Anna. I'm a senior in the
School of Foreign Service. I'm studying
science, technology, and international
affairs. Really quickly, I wanted to
thank Dr. Hinton for your decades of
tireless work, even through all the AI
winters and everything. But now for the
question. You alluded earlier to the
debate between the um, you know,
connectionist and the symbolist and um
kind of famously in the beginning,
Microsoft dismissed the connectionist
and you some of your work. So, I was
wondering if you think right now in the
scientific field, do you think there's a
similar type of neglect or dismissal of
any school of thought for not policy
makers, but anyone in the field? Um,
thank you very much.
Okay, I'm not the guy to ask, because
the approach I pushed is currently
winning. Um
The people to ask
I mean, it's quite possible there'll be
a very different approach. Um
And the people to ask are young people
who think what I'm doing is wrong. Um,
but I'm going to stick with what's
working.
Okay. Sorry, that's not a very good
answer, but um there may well be
radically different approaches out
there, but it's not old men who are
going to push them.
All right, thanks. Back down here.
Hi, my name is Charlotte. I'm a junior
in the college studying government and
psychology and I'm from Connecticut. And
uh one concern about AI that we haven't
yet discussed today is its ability to
spread misinformation,
um specifically like via voice
replication, accurate videos, et cetera.
And this information will absolutely
worsen our already very deep and
disturbing political divides. So, I was
wondering what you would propose as
policy to address this issue or what you
foresee being
put on the docket to deal with. Okay.
Um, I have something to say about that.
Um, many people suggest we should get AI
to recognize things like fake videos.
That's never going to work.
The The first AI systems that generated
really good images were called
generative adversarial networks. And the
problem is, if you have an AI that can
recognize that a video is fake,
then a generative AI can look inside
that other AI and figure out how to
generate things that it will think are
real. And so, you get this sort of arms
race between a discriminative AI that
says whether they're fake or not and a
generative AI that's getting better and
better at fooling the discriminative AI.
And that's how you got very good images
with generative adversarial networks.
So, there's no future, I believe, no
long-term future in getting AI to
recognize
fakes produced by AI, cuz you can always
make better fakes then. The way to do it
is to have provenance.
So, a few hundred years ago in Britain,
there were political pamphlets and the
government insisted that every pamphlet
that was printed had the printer's name
on it. Cuz if you had the printer's
name, you could find out who paid the
printer and you could find out the
provenance of the pamphlet. And that's
cuz the printing press was a limitation.
For at least for political videos,
there's a scheme suggested to me by Jan
Tallinn,
who's I should mention Jan Tallinn. He's
invented Skype um with some other
people. Sold it to Microsoft. He's a
billionaire. He's used a lot of his
money for AI safety. Many, many AI
safety groups are funded by Jan Tallinn.
Um, he's taking it very seriously.
Um, he suggested you do the following.
Every political video,
you have a QR code at the beginning. The
QR code takes you to a website. Websites
are unique. Um, if on that webs if that
is the website of the political campaign
and on that website, there's the
identical video, you know it's for real.
If not, you know it's not. And your
browser can do all that work. Your
browser can take the QR code, go to the
website, check if it's the website of
that campaign, um check if there's an
identical video. So, it should be
possible for your browser to tell you
that this is a genuine video for that
campaign, at least. Um
You have to go for provenance, not
recognizing fakes.
Um
I once gave this argument to people from
the New York Times, who thought that was
great, because I mean, I I believe news
that comes from the New York Times, the
BBC, the Guardian, people I believe will
get two sources, at least two sources,
and won't just make stuff up. Um,
occasionally get stuff wrong, but
it's all going to be done by provenance,
I believe, in the long run.
Well, somebody
I am told by my staff that there was
I was on television selling on on the
internet selling some insurance policy.
And it sounded and looked very much like
me. So, it is a real
real issue. And you just worry that, you
know, 2 weeks before an election an
election
and they're very good at this stuff. You
can have somebody uh sounding like
somebody
uh saying crazy stuff, which can impact
an election. So, it's a a very big issue
and I think it's got to be dealt with.
And I actually think we should use
inoculation. That is, before an
election, people should put out very
convincing fake videos,
fake videos in favor of Trump, fake
videos against Trump. Um, and at the end
of the fake video, they should say,
"That was a fake video." What they're
trying to do is make you understand that
fake videos will be out there. And it's
like inoculation. They give you one
that's labeled as fake, so you can get
used to dealing with it.
Like media literacy. Yeah.
Thank you.
Thanks.
Uh, okay. Back up to the balcony.
Um, hi. My name is Ryan Lee. I'm a
senior studying international politics
and journalism.
Um I wanted to talk about the Department
of Education um with the administration
taking further steps to dismantle it
today.
Um Dr. Hinton, you earlier mentioned the
importance of federal grants in in
fields like AI. So, I wanted to ask you
what you think the future of especially
money in AI is with the federal
government taking a further step back.
Um and to you, Senator Sanders, um this
is something that that can only
officially done by an act of Congress.
So, how do you expect Congress's role to
be seen here and um how do you expect
them to react?
So, um I think if you really wanted to
make America weak,
what you would do is you'd attack the
research universities and you'd cut off
funding for basic research. It won't
have an immediate effect. So, if you
look where all this deep learning came
from, it came from long-term funding of
basic research over many years.
Um if you cut off that money, it's like
eating the seed corn. In 10, 20 years'
time, America will be way behind China.
So, what the Trump administration is
doing is
precisely what you'd do if you wanted to
make America weak. So, that's the first
point. The second point is
um
well, you have a Secretary of Education
who thought that AI was A1.
And there's a video where she's calling
it A1, which is kind of extraordinary
because that means for a long time she
must have thought that AI was A1.
Um
she didn't go to university. I think
maybe she doesn't understand that AI was
the initials for something, artificial
intelligence. She got confused with the
um the the fact that a one is a bit like
an I.
Um
I don't know.
If if you've got a Secretary of
Education like that, I don't know what
to say.
Well,
let me just
say this that of the panoply of problems
facing this country,
uh education is at
at the top of the list, I think.
Uh right now in the richest country in
the history of the world,
we have a child care system which is
basically dysfunctional.
So, zero to four are the most important
years of development
uh intellectual and emotional
development for a human being.
And yet we have people who are working
with those kids who make less than a
McDonald's worker.
Uh which says a lot about how we not
only regard education, but how we regard
our children. That's number one.
Uh number two, uh some of you may be
familiar that international exams,
reading, science,
uh
uh math, uh we do very poorly uh
compared to other countries around the
world.
Uh
we are having a very difficult time, for
good reason, attracting the best and the
brightest to go into public schools
right now. Being a teacher is an
enormously difficult job. We're not
giving teachers the support that they
need.
As many of you are aware of, the cost of
higher education is outrageously high.
Many of you are going to be graduating
with tens and tens of thousands of debt.
Go to medical school, go to graduate
school, it's going to be even more than
that.
So, getting back to Dr. Hinton's point,
if we in fact want to make America
great,
it is not an exaggeration to say that we
want the best educated people in the
world. That we prize education, that we
respect educators,
and that we want to make sure that every
person in this country has the ability
to get all of the education they need to
succeed in life. That's good for them,
that is good for the country.
But we are moving in every direction in
exactly the wrong way.
My friend, Mr. Mondani, who's going to
be mayor of New York soon,
[Music]
has been
he has been attacked because he thinks
that in New York City child care should
be free.
What a radical idea.
We give a trillion dollars in tax breaks
to the 1%.
We spend a trillion dollars on the
military, but the idea that we have
high-quality free child care, oh God
forbid,
in America, we do what was the case 70
years ago and make our major public
colleges and universities tuition free,
that's considered to be radical.
So, I think we need to take a deep
breath
and say that if we really want to
be a great nation, we've got to respect
education, we've got to adequately fund
education, and we've got to make sure
that educational opportunity is
available to all.
All right. Thanks for the question.
I I I would like to just add something
to that.
If you look when America was great in
the like the
50s and early 60s, America was
developing very fast and people could
afford two cars and a home and things
like that.
The tax rates on the rich were something
like 70% at that point.
Um that's what you need. You need taxes
to fund these things and you need to
stop the rich evading taxes. Um it's
it's just crazy. They can easily afford
to pay the taxes. They'll they'll end up
with only a few billions to dispose of.
Um you don't need that much money.
All right.
We are running low on time and I always
hate to say this when we've got long
lines, but we've got time for one more
student question. So, we'll come down
here.
>> on me then. Apologies to the rest of
you, especially you at the mic up there.
So, you've got to ask the most brilliant
question of all.
No pressure. Yeah, I know, right? Uh I'm
Nicholas. I'm a first-year graduate
student at the McCourt School of Public
Policy and I'm from New York City and uh
my question is for both of you, which is
do you think that the AI replacing
entry-level positions will kind of
create like a talent doom cycle where we
accidentally stop creating experts
because we're not investing in these
entry-level workers so that they can
become experts in their fields?
No. No? Okay. And I think what's
happening I think what will happen is AI
is developing fast enough that it'll
develop fast enough to fill any gaps.
I just worry um
you know, when I hear the word hear
folks talking about building millions of
robots
and at the same time saying they want to
rebuild manufacturing in America, for
example,
you can rebuild manufacturing in
America, but you're not going to have
workers doing the work and I worry
you know, point that Dr. Hinton made
earlier in in the program,
who the hell how do people going to get
an income to buy the products that are
being sold?
And in terms of uh AI in the world that
you are living in, I do what worry very
much that if entry-level jobs
are not going to be there for you, how
do you
move up and progress up the up the
ladder? So, it is a a real concern. Let
me let me, if I might, Mo, just
ask the people here,
just raise your hand.
Uh let me see how to frame this
question.
Do you see or it'll be a I'm going to
ask you two questions. The first one is
for your own lives as young people,
do you see AI as a positive development
for your future? Raise your hand.
Okay. Same question. Are you concerned
about it being a negative impact on your
future?
Wow.
Okay, most of the hands went up when I
go I would tell you this,
uh and Dr. Hinton, where I became I'm
not even on any of the committees in
Congress that deal with this stuff, but
I
got involved. I went around the country
uh recently
and uh I was in Davenport, Iowa and I
speaking before working-class audience.
And in the course of
a speech,
you know, I said, "I'm just curious."
And I asked the same exact question as I
asked you. I said, "Working-class
audience, I said, tell me, do you think
AI and robotics is going to be a
positive development for you?"
In a room of about 2,500 people, two
hands went up.
So, I think among working-class people,
there is a legitimate and real
and I think based on reality, concern
about what AI will do.
And I'm hearing that in this room uh
from many of you as well.
Senator and Professor, I want to ask
each of you to share any final thoughts
you have, but one question I'd ask you
to weave in to your final thoughts,
what does the average person do?
Right? What can these students
do
to prepare for everything you've been
talking about?
I think in many ways that that question,
Mo, goes beyond AI.
It really is a political question.
And as we have said a dozen times, AI is
neither good nor bad. It depends on who
benefits and how it is used.
Right now in this country,
you are living in what I refer to as an
oligarchic form of society
where a small number of very powerful
people, people who are moving
aggressively in the area of AI, but they
were powerful before they did that,
have enormous control over the economy
and
the political life of this country
through their ability. Musk, for
example, contributed 270 million dollars
to make Trump the president.
So, it is not only AI, it is not only
climate change, it's not only the
economy, it's not only health care. You
are living in the richest country in the
history of the world.
And if we had a rational system
designed to improve life for all people,
there are extraordinary things that we
could be doing. AI is going to make us
wealthier.
Yes, education could be free from child
care to graduate school. Yes, we could
have universal health care. Yes, we
could lead the world in transforming our
energy system. Yes, we could build the
units of affordable and low-income
housing that we need. This is not
utopian radical ideas. We could do it if
you have a government that is concerned
about the needs of ordinary people. If
you have a government concerned and
dominated by the rich, they will get tax
breaks. They will get deregulation.
They will be able to produce more carbon
emissions, et cetera. So, the real
question to me is a fundamental
political question. And we need your
generation.
And we're seeing progress, I got to tell
you, all over the country, standing up
and creating a government that works for
all of us and not just the big money
interest. That to me is the issue.
[Applause]
[Music]
Professor, for those of us that are not
programmers or engineers, what can we do
to get ready?
Um
what I have to say is basically what
Bernie said.
Okay.
Um I can't thank each of you enough for
joining us tonight and kickstarting this
conversation, not that it needed to be
kickstarted. Students here are coming
into our office and many others talking
and asking and thinking about AI on a
daily basis. I want to thank um the
student volunteers from GU Politics as
well as from the Computer Science and
Massive Data Institute programs
who are helped us put this together
tonight. But most importantly, even more
importantly than thanking these two, I
want to thank all of you for coming out
tonight, sharing part of your evening,
and asking such great questions and
engaging. Thank you all very much. Have
a great night.
[Applause]