Thanks very much for joining me to
discuss a very important issue.
Artificial intelligence and robotics
will transform the world.
It will bring unimaginable changes to
our economy, our politics, warfare,
foreign policy, our emotional
well-being, our environment, and how we
educate and raise our children. Further
unbelievable but true. There is a very
real fear that in the not tooistant
future a super intelligent AI could
replace human beings in controlling the
planet. That's not science fiction. That
is a real fear that very knowledgeable
people have.
Despite the extraordinarily
extraordinary importance of this issue
and the speed at which it is
progressing, AI is getting far too
little discussion in Congress, the
media, and within the general
population. And that has got to change
now. Several months ago, as the ranking
member of the US Senate Committee on
Health, Education, Labor, and Pensions,
I undertook an investigation regarding
the monumental challenges that we face
with the rapid development of artificial
intelligence.
And very recently, I held a public
discussion at Georgetown University with
Nobel Prize winner Dr. Jeffrey Hinton
considered to be the godfather of AI,
the guy who really brought this uh
subject to the place that it is now to
get his views on a wide range of AI
related subjects.
Based on our investigation
and other information that we are
gathering, my staff and I will soon be
presenting a very specific set of
recommendations to Congress as to how we
can begin addressing some of the
unprecedented threats that AI poses.
Here are just some of the outstanding
questions that we intend to answer in
our report.
First and maybe most importantly, who
should be in charge of the
transformation into an AI world?
Currently, a handful of the very
wealthiest people on Earth, Elon Musk,
Jeff Bezos, Bill Gates, Mark Zuckerberg,
Peter Teal, and others are investing
many, many hundreds of billions of
dollars in developing and implementing
AI and robotics.
Are we comfortable with seeing these
enormously powerful men, handful of
people, shape the future of humanity
without any democratic input or
oversight?
Is the goal of the AI revolution simply
to make the very very richest people on
Earth even richer and even more
powerful? or will this revolutionary
technology be utilized to benefit all of
humanity? That is the question. Who
benefits from this incredible
transformation of society?
Why does Donald Trump, who is strongly
supporting these big tech oligarchs,
want to impose an executive order
blocking states from regulating AI? Why
does Peter Teal, the billionaire
investor and co-founder of Palunteer,
call those who want regulations over AI
quote, legionnaires of the Antichrist,
end quote?
Does this elite group of
multi-billionaire big tech guys really
believe that they have the divine right
to rule? Are we going back to the 19th
century where you had in those days
kings and monarchs saying God gave them
the right to rule? Is that what these
guys are saying today? How far will they
go to resist government regulation? So
that's one huge issue that we've got to
get deeply involved in. Further, what
impact will AI and robotics have on our
economy and the lives of working people?
The report that I released last month
found that AI, automation, and robotics
could replace nearly 100 million jobs in
America over the next decade, including
40% of registered nurses, 47% of truck
drivers, 64% of accountants, 65% of
teaching assistants, and 89%
of fast food workers, among many other
occupations that will
hit hard by AI and robotics.
Now, Elon Musk recently said that quote,
"AI and robots will replace all jobs.
Working will be optional." End quote.
Bill Gates predicted that humans quote
won't be needed for much for most things
end quote. Dario Amodi, the CEO of
Anthropic, warned that AI could lead to
the loss of half of all entry-level
white collar jobs.
If AI and robotics eliminate millions of
jobs and create massive unemployment,
how will people survive if they have no
income? How do they feed their families
or pay for housing or healthcare?
Is government doing anything now to
prepare for this potential economic
disaster?
Further,
what impact will AI have on our
democracy?
At a time when the foundations of
democracy are under attack here in the
United States and throughout the world,
will AI and robotics help make us become
a freer, more democratic society, or
will it give even more power to the
oligarchs who control the technology?
Will a AI result in a massive invasion
of our privacy and our civil liberties?
Larry Ellison, the second richest person
on earth, predicted an AI powered
surveillance state where, quote,
"Citizens will be on their best behavior
because we're constantly recording and
reporting everything that is going on."
End of quote. This is the second
wealthiest guy on earth investing
hundreds of billions in AI.
Are we reaching the stage
where every phone call that we make,
every email and text that we send, every
bit of research we do on the internet
will be available to the owners of AI?
And if that is the case, how do we
sustain a democracy under those
conditions? How do we protect our
privacy?
Further, could AI literally redefine,
and this is almost crazy stuff, very
unimaginable, but could AI literally
redefine
what it means to be a human being?
Who we are and how we develop
emotionally and intellectually is highly
dependent upon our relationships with
other human beings, our parents, of
course, our family, teachers, lovers,
friends, and co-workers. To quote the
17th century poet John Dunn, you all
remember this poem. Quote, "No man is an
island unto himself." End quote. The
human beings with whom we interact help
shape us to become for better or for
worse the people we are. But AI is in
the process of changing that. According
to a recent poll by Common Sense Media,
72% of US teenagers say they have used
AI for companionship
and more than half of them do so
regularly.
What does it mean? I want you to think
about this. What does it mean for young
people to form friendships with AI and
become increasingly isolated from other
human beings, spend enormous amount of
time on their screens talking to AI
characters?
What happens when millions around the
world seek emotional support from a
machine?
What is the long-term impact upon our
humanity when our most important
relationships are not with other human
beings?
Further,
what impact is AI having on our
environment?
AI data centers require a massive huge
amount of electricity and water. A
relatively small AI data center can
consume more electricity than 80,000
homes. A large one like the 165 billion
data center that Open AI and Oracle are
building in Abalene, Texas will use as
much electricity as 750,000
homes, one data center.
Meta is building a data center in
Louisiana the size of Manhattan that
will use as much electricity as
1,200,000 homes.
In community after community, Americans
are fighting back against data centers
being built by some of the largest and
most powerful corporations in the world.
They are opposing the destruction of
their local environment,
soaring electric bills, and the
diversion of scarce water supplies.
Nationally,
how will continued construction of AI
data centers impact our environment?
Further,
how will AI and robotics impact foreign
policy and warfare? Well, maybe you
haven't thought about that.
But the reality is that sadly,
tragically, in the midst of the 21st
century, governments have not yet
created a mechanism for solving
international or internal disputes
without armed conflict. We are seeing
terrible wars taking place right now.
Nonetheless,
government leaders are often hesitant
about going to war because of their fear
of public reaction to the loss of life.
No politician
wants to go before his or her people and
say, "Oh, sorry. We've lost thousands of
dollars of young men and women."
But what happens when you have robots
replacing
human beings in the act of warfare? You
have robot armies.
What does the future look like if
millions of robot soldiers replace human
beings? Will leaders be more likely to
engage in war or threaten military
action if they don't have to worry about
loss of life? Will there be literally an
arms race in robots? So you can see
country fighting country not with their
own human beings, not with their own
soldiers, but with robots. And if you
don't have to worry about losing robots
as opposed to losing human beings, how
will this shape foreign policies around
the world? It's a big issue. Doesn't get
a lot of discussion.
Further, and needless to say, of some
consequence,
is AI an existential threat to human
control over the planet?
Now, some of us remember the scene, and
I know there've been a different movies
making the same point, but some of us
remember that scene in that great 1968
science fiction film 2001, A Space
Odyssey, in which HAL, the super
intelligent computer that controlled the
spaceship, rebelss against its human
masters.
Today, is AI makes rapid progress. Dr.
Jeff Jeffrey Hinton recently told me
that it was only a matter of time before
AI becomes smarter than human beings.
Now, what's the impact of that? Does
that raise the possibility that humans
will actually lose their ability to
control the planet? And if that becomes
a possibility, how do how do we stop
that extraordinary threat?
And let me just tell you these are just
some underlying sum of the questions
that must be answered as AI and robotics
rapidly progress. Remember these guys
have spent hundreds and hundreds of
billions. There are breakthroughs almost
every day.
AI and robotics are revolutionary
technologies
that will bring about an unprecedented
transformation of society.
Will these changes be positive and
improve life for ordinary Americans
or will they be disastrous?
In my view, Congress must act now. We've
got to start answering these questions
and other questions. We need to have a
national discussion. This is a huge
issue and maybe the people on top, the
billionaires who control the technology
want us to ignore it. But for the future
of our world, our kids, the environment,
etc., this is an issue that cannot be
ignored. So, we're going to work
together. Look forward to hearing from
you about this issue. But let's go
forward in attempting to answer some of
these questions. So, thank you all very
much.