for being here. The congresswoman and I
going to be chatting about
an enormously important issue.
Let me start off by saying
that in my view and in the view of
people who know a lot more about this
issue than I do,
we are at the beginning of the most
profound technological revolution in
world history. Period. The most profound
technological revolution in world
history. a revolution that will bring
unimaginable changes to our society in a
relatively short period of time.
Artificial intelligence and robotics
will impact our economy, our democracy,
our privacy rights, our emotional
well-being, our environment, and even
our very survival as human beings on
this planet. The scale, scope and speed
of this transformation will be
unprecedented.
According to Demis
Hashibus, who is the head of Google deep
mine, the AI revolution will be 10 times
bigger than the industrial revolution
and 10 times faster. In other words,
AI and robotics will have a hund times
impact in terms of what the industrial
revolution did. And it's not just what
AI companies are saying, it's what they
are doing.
This year alone, four major AI companies
are expected to spend roughly 670
billion dollars building data centers
and tens of billions more on research
and development.
Despite the extraordinary importance of
this issue and its impact on every man,
woman, and child in this country, AI has
received far too little serious
discussion here in our nation's capital.
I fear that Congress is totally
unprepared for the magnitude of the
changes that are already taking place.
While Congress has not paid attention or
enough attention to this issue, the
American people have. According to a
recent poll, 79% of voters are concerned
that the government does not have a plan
to protect workers from AI job losses.
That same poll also found that 56% of
voters, majority of voters are concerned
about losing their job or having someone
in their family lose their jobs in the
next year, not in the next 10 years, in
the next year.
Why are the American people so
concerned?
And the answer is they have a lot of
reasons to be concerned. They understand
that at a time of massive income and
wealth inequality
when the billionaire class has never
ever had it so good, some 60% of our
people are living paycheck to paycheck.
And the American people understand that
the AI revolution, these massive
investments are being driven by some of
the wealthiest people in our country and
the world. People like Elon Musk, Jeff
Bezos, Mark Zuckerberg, and Larry
Ellison.
They understand that these billionaires
are investing huge amounts of money into
AI and robotics, not to improve life for
working families, but to dramatically
increase their own wealth and power. Do
you think the average American is
sitting around trusting that the
multi-billionaires
are going to transform society for the
good of ordinary people? I don't think
so. In terms of the impact that AI and
robotics will have on working people,
let us listen to what the tech oligarchs
themselves are saying. Not the
congresswoman, not me. Let's hear what
the tech oligarchs are themselves
saying. Elon Musk, who has made massive
investments in AI and robotics, has
stated, and I quote,
"AI robots will replace all jobs."
That's about it. Replace all jobs. Bill
Gates, another massive who's also made
massive investments, has said humans,
quote, won't be needed for most things
end quote. and Mustafa Solman of
Microsoft AI predicts that most white
collar work could be automated within
the next decade.
What we are talking about therefore is
the possibility that AI and automation
could displace tens of millions of
workers in the United States from their
current employment. We already seeing
early signs of this transformation with
declining employment in AI exposed
occupations and growing difficulty for
young people entering the workforce.
If machines can perform most
economically valuable work better than
humans and that is the goal that
machines will be able to do the job you
are doing better than you are doing. If
that happens, pretty simple question.
What happens to the workers?
How do people earn a living?
How do they support their families? And
how do programs like Social Security and
Medicare survive without a stable tax
base? People are not working. They're
not paying taxes. And let me ask a very
simple question that is on the minds of
millions of Americans.
How will workers who lose their jobs
find new employment if there are no jobs
available?
What happens to the over six million
truck drivers, cab drivers, ride share
drivers, and bus drivers of virtually if
virtually all transportation is
conducted through driverless vehicles,
which under present terms seems likely
to happen.
What happens to the young college
graduates who today going out looking
for an entry-level job but that job is
not there? And let me say this maybe
from personal experience.
I have seen this before and the American
working class has seen this process play
out before.
In the 1990s, the working class of this
country was told by the corporate world,
by the elites, by the corporate media,
don't worry about unfeted free trade. My
god, NAFTA, PNTR, with China, it is
going to create millions and millions of
good paying jobs. Man, Democrats,
Republicans,
corporate executives, everybody came
together. Free trade going to be the
best thing that ever happened to
American workers. Well, not quite.
What happened in fact is that thousands
and thousands of factories in this
country were shut down and what happened
is that millions of workers lost their
jobs. So we have been
we have seen this play out in the past.
But when we talk about AI and robotics,
we're not just talking about the
economy. AI is already reshaping how we
as human beings relate to each other.
According to a recent poll by Common
Sense Media, 72% of American teenagers
say they have used AI for companionship
and more than half do so regularly.
What does it mean for young people to
form friendships
with AI
and become more and more lonely and
isolated from other human beings?
Everybody understands we have a major
mental health crisis for our young
people right now. I fear that AI could
make it even worse.
And then when we talk about what's going
on, we also have to talk about privacy.
Larry Ellison, second richest person on
earth who's gobbling up a lot of the
media in this country, who is a major
investor in AI, predicts an AI powered
surveillance state is coming where, this
is Larry Ellison, major investor. This
is what he says.
Where citizens will be on their best
behavior because we're constantly
recording and reporting everything that
is going on. End quote. That's your
phone calls, your texts, your emails,
the websites that you visit. It will be
recorded if we continue the current
trends. Further, AI is undermining
American democracy. the rise of deep
fakes
where you have very convincing fake
images. It happened to me. I don't know
if did it happen to you? All right.
Where they had me selling some rebates
or something like that. Looked very
good. Almost convinced me, but it wasn't
me. Uh we're seeing fake videos, fake
audios.
What happens when a day before the
election, somebody who looks like the
candidate gets up and says something
outrageous and people believe it?
If people cannot trust what they see and
hear, informed decisionmaking becomes
nearly impossible. It will become harder
and harder to distinguish between truth
and untruth.
There is also in what we're seeing now a
significant environmental cost. AI
requires enormous computing power,
driving the expansion of energy and
water intensive data centers, increasing
electricity demand, and potentially
deepening reliance on fossil fuels in
the midst of a climate crisis.
Finally, and let me say this, and and I
know some people out there may still
think this is science fiction, but it
ain't. I have talked to some of the
leading scientists and most
knowledgeable people in the world about
the potential existential threats that
AI brings to the human race including
Jeffrey Hinton. Some of you may know
that Dr. Hinton who is a Nobel Prize
winner in physics. He's considered to be
the godfather of AI. He's worked on this
thing for decades. They have cautioned
us that AI could soon surpass human
intelligence and operate independently
beyond our control. And if that happens,
what they acknowledge is it poses a
profound threat to the very survival of
the human race. So what is happening in
Washington right now in response to all
of these enormous concerns? Well, we
learned just today that Donald Trump uh
has appointed a commission which is made
up of the very people who are going to
financially benefit from AI and robotics
including some of the wealthiest people
in the world like Mr. Ellison, Mr.
Zuckerberg,
uh and the video uh the video CEO Dennis
Wong, Jensen Wong. And needless to say,
there is no reputation on that
commission of workers or
environmentalists or consumers. And that
is why in my view, we need a very
different approach. Across the country,
communities are already pushing back
against the unchecked expansion of data
centers. More than 100 localities have
enacted moratoriums or restrictions, and
states are beginning to take action as
well. Importantly, and this is a very
important point, leaders within the AI
industry have called for a pause. The
guys who know the most about the threats
of the development of AI and robotics,
they robotics, they have called for a
pause. In 2023, just about three years
ago, over 1,000 experts, including Elon
Musk, uh called for AI Labs to quote,
"Immediately pause for at least 6 months
end quote." And if such pause were not
enacted, and clearly a pause was not
enacted, they called on governments
quote to step in and institute a
moratorum.
They understood what is at stake.
Congresswoman Alexandria Kaziocortez and
I understand what is at stake. That is
why today we are announcing legislation
to impose a moratorium on the
construction of new AI data centers
until strong national safeguards are in
place to ensure that
AI is safe and effective. That means the
government reviews and approves AI
products before they are released.
Further, that the economic gains of AI
and robotics will benefit ordinary
Americans and not just the billionaire
owners of the industry. Further, that AI
data centers do not increase electricity
or utility prices, harm communities, or
destroy the environment. Importantly,
this legislation would also impose a ban
on the export of AI chips to any country
without such protections, including
China. A moratorum will give us time.
Time to understand the risks, time to
protect working families, time to defend
our democracy, and time to ensure that
technology works for all of us, not just
the few. So with that, let me now
introduce the Congresswoman from New
York, Congresswoman Alexandria
Kaziocortez.
>> Thank you.
>> Thank you, Senator. Um, first and
foremost, I want to take a moment to
express my GA uh gratitude to Senator
Sanders for bringing us together today
to introduce this critical legislation.
Within just a matter of short years, AI
has become often forcibly integrated
into many aspects of American existence,
into our doctor's offices, our
government, and oftentimes to the
detriment of working people. Last year
alone, AI was responsible for over
54,000
layoffs nationwide.
And when we talk about those jobs, it's
not just a number. These are industries.
These are communities. These are
families.
You know, just a four a few short years
ago, Sam Alman came before Congress.
And in a direct plea, he begged us to
regulate this industry, he said that
these tools were under no circumstances
ready nor should they be integrated into
weapons of war. they that we must uh
impose severe regulations immediately to
prevent mass layoffs and to ensure that
any productivity that comes of this
industry can benefit working people.
Three short years later, none of that
has happened. And in fact, in many
cases, the opposite has happened.
I'll start with another quote from Sam
Alman who said 10 years ago AI will
probably lead to the end of the world
but in the meantime there will be great
companies created with serious machine
learning.
Uh while I am happy that Mr. Altman is
responsible uh on his end of the deal.
You know, he has his responsibilities on
the company side. Our responsibility is
to take care of people and that is what
we're here to do today.
Unfortunately, the leaders of this
industry have repeated time and time
again that they view working people as
an unless as an endless untapped market
to be manipulated and exploited. that
they would sell our country out if it
meant that they could turn a profit. And
it is no surprise that in the four years
since Chat GPT was released, we have
seen AI deployed at a massive scale to
create big brotherlike surveillance.
Every day, Americans are seeing videos
of ICE agents waving phones into crowds,
threatening that if they use their First
Amendment rights, US citizens using
their First Amendment rights, that they
will be added to some vague database
that the American people have not
consented to nor are knowledgeable
about.
Companies like Palunteer are mining
endlessly the data and privacy of the
American people, keeping track of
everything that they say and do, and
sending it all to a militarized and
centralized government.
When you take the subway, when you share
a Tik Tok, when you talk to your Alexa
at home, they are collecting your data
and figuring out new ways to weaponize
it. And now they are using AI tools to
automate this so that it is not only
pervasive but that it is effortless.
We must sound the alarm now. And because
of this surveillance of the American
people is not going to stop. We must
stop it. All of this harm has occurred
not in spite of but because of the
absence of federal legislation to
regulate AI. This is not my first bill
about around AI and I can tell you that
it is extremely discouraging
to see how even the most minute efforts
to protect people at some of the
smallest and most basic level like
trying to prevent AI generated child
pornography
is still combed oftentimes by many
people here on the hill and throughout
industry.
In this story, currently the story of AI
is a story of corruption. It is fueled
and funded by the same multi-billion
dollar corporations lobbying politicians
to sit back and do nothing while they
harm our communities. In fact, one of
the largest explosions of super PAC and
outside funding is by the AI industry.
And for years, Congress has enabled this
permission structure. a permission
structure that allows billionaires like
Sam Alman, Elon Musk, and Peter Teal to
be trusted to regulate themselves under
the guise of quote American innovation.
And what are they asking for now?
Endless energy. These companies are now
so desperate to profit off of the AI
boom that they are racing to construct
thousands of giant AI data centers and
jacking up the utility costs of everyday
Americans to pay for it. These data
centers power thousands of highintensity
computer chips that are processing at
all times and require massive amounts of
energy to operate. Just one hypers scale
data center consumes the same amount of
energy in one second as 100,000
households.
Because of the massive amounts of energy
they use, power and water utility
companies must build multi-billion
dollar infrastructure to keep up with
the demand. And these companies are not
paying for their own energy
infrastructure. People's energy bills
around the country are skyrocketing
in order to pay for these AI data
centers for them. In the last 5 years,
Americans who live near data centers saw
their electric bills increase over $267%
each month. We are talking about an $80
in a monthly increase from $80 a month
to $294
a month. Working people are already
living paycheck to paycheck in some
states off of wages as low as $7.25
an hour, another federal minimum wage
that Congress also refuses to raise.
They simply cannot afford another
increase to their monthly bills. And
this results in people cutting corners
whenever they can to keep the lights on,
whether it's skipping meals or rationing
their insulin. And while the American
people are suffering, big tech continues
to demand more. More data centers, more
energy, more data collection, more
American jobs replaced by AI. All on the
feet of the American people to pay.
And across the country, Democrats,
Republicans, and independents are
standing up. People are standing up to
big tech and saying no to these data
centers being built in their own
communities. More than 100 local
communities across 12 states have
already enacted local moratoriums on
data centers and Congress itself has a
moral obligation to stand with them and
stop big tech from ruining their
communities. Our legislation in the
House and the Senate would hit the
brakes on construction of new data
centers until we address several of the
key areas of harm AI poses. Our bills
learn from our lack of regulation
following the similar rise uh regarding
the internet and demands a new approach
to AI. One that protects the American
people from big tech's egregious
overreach. One bound by our shared
commitment over those who wish to patent
it. One that centers prosperity for the
many over exorbitant profits for the
very few. Thank you.
>> Okay, far away. By the way, we're just
going to take questions on AI. Uh yes,
who are you? And
>> Brian, this is um one of the most common
critiques that comes up when this idea
of raised is that we're in an AI race
with China and that slowing down the
progress of AI development anyway would
give China an advantage whether that's
economic national security. I'm curious,
you know, when that critique is raised
to you, what do you say to that? Is that
something you're concerned? Well, I
think the good news here and it's not
widely known is there are a number of
Chinese scientists who share the same
concern that American scientists
uh are worried about and that is if we
don't get a handle on AI there going to
be enormous existential consequences. So
I think in a sane world what happens is
the leadership of the United States sits
down with the leadership in China and
leadership around the world to work
together so that we don't go over the
edge and create a technology which could
perhaps destroy humanity. But I would
say there are Chinese scientists fairly
high up in the government who share
those concerns. We've got to immediately
with a sense of urgency uh bring those
people together. Anything you want to
ask?
>> I mean
I think the concern uh there is easily
remedied by passing protections for
people. We need to sort out uh energy
sources. Once these companies can be on
the up and up, providing their own
energy, building out and investing in
the infrastructure, refusing to free
ride off of the American people, then we
can continue to develop and explore this
technology. I don't think that this is
about a denialism of science or uh
American competitiveness, but it is
about an integration of protection of
the American people um instead of
allowing this to happen at their
expense.
>> And furthermore, this legislation will
prohibit the export of chips um to China
and other countries. Yes, sir. Nick,
>> the congresswoman
from Fox Business, you mentioned 267%
electric bills of the administration has
taken some steps to remedy these
concerns. I wonder what you make of
their actions. My second question for
both of you is do either of you guys use
artificial intelligence in your everyday
lives?
>> So uh you know in terms of the impact
that it's having. I think we just need
to ask everyday people on if they're
feeling the effects of that. I think um
as much as you know as much as we'd have
as I personally have differences with
this administration, I would want them
to be successful in reducing the energy
bills of American people, but people
aren't feeling it. It's not working. Um
in New York City alone, there are some
families that are getting you electric
bills that are $600 a month, as high as
some people were paying in rent not too
long ago before our housing costs uh
skyrocketed as well. So um so you know I
I don't think those efforts are working
on behalf of the administration. As far
as AI, I I do not regularly integrate it
into my daily life. Um but I know many
people do. I think our job tends to be a
little bit more for me. My job a lot of
my job is quite writing based and I like
to do my own.
>> Thank you.
>> Very oldfashioned.
>> I'm old fashioned that way. Um to answer
the question, uh we have looked at AI.
We did a chat with Claude
um recently. Um uh but I I don't use it
on a regular basis. Uh other questions?
Anyone else? Yes.
>> Huffington Post. Senator, do you think
the Democratic Party is taking the
threat of AI seriously enough? And can
you talk a little bit about AI's
influence in elections? A lot of money
in
>> Thank you. No, I don't think the
Democratic Party leadership is taking
this issue anywhere near as serious
seriously as it should. We need to
develop a sense of urgency here. The
economic impacts are going to be
enormous. The impacts on our children
will be enormous. And again, there is
literally an existential threat to the
existence of the human race. Now you
tell me, do you think that leadership
here on either side of the aisle, you're
saying, "Whoa, we better get moving on
this thing." The answer is no. And the
second point, the question you're
raising that the congresswoman
mentioned, let us be clear. Why is
Congress not moving aggressively? Well,
maybe it has something to do with 150
million and more that is coming in to
Congress in campaign contributions and
in super PACs. When you have a class of
people who are multi-billionaires
spending a few hundred million dollars
on elections is chicken feed. Okay? And
that is what they are doing. So what
they're saying to members of Congress
and candidates, you're going to stand up
to us. Well, guess what? There's going
to be a $20 million ad campaign coming
tomorrow starting against you. That's
the reality.
Other questions? Yes, sir.
against so it's been said that the data
centers and the chip makers and the app
makers have kind of created this
circular you know loan and business
basically and that it's created a bubble
and by pulling out of it we could have
serious economic how do we pull out of
that and another question is what do you
make of cla
>> your first question it's an important
question it's a little bit different
than what we're talking about today
you're talking about the possibility of
a bubble burst having enormous economic
impact I think that's true. But above
and beyond that, what we're talking
about is a technology bubble or no
bubble that is uh going to have a real
impact on American societies. He asked
me about uh my chat with Claude. I'll
tell you it was a little bit
mind-blowing.
You can very easily and again I suppose
the young people have more familiarity
with it than uh than I do. It is
amazingly easy to start seeing this
entity, this AI agent or call it what
you might as a human being. And please
remember importantly
AI is only going to get more and more
effective in years to come. It's only a
relatively few years old. And yet you
sit down and you can absolutely Hey,
have a nice day. How are you? I'm pretty
good. How are you doing? Okay, you can
get into that. And I want you to think
about what it will mean to a 13-year-old
girl who is struggling
and having AI as her best friend or a
15year-old boy or whatever it may be.
These are real serious dangers. But to
answer your question, it is mind-blowing
how quickly you can somehow see this as
a human agent.
Okay. Yes,
>> there's some other ideas that are being
it to
make it as you kind ofuded it so that
these companies are paying for their own
producing their own energy. Why not go
that route? Why
>> because that's one part of the problem.
Uh as the congresswoman mentioned,
you're seeing people now whose electric
bills are soaring beyond control. That
is an issue that we've got to deal with.
But there are other profound issues. So
if somehow or another that was put under
control and electric bills did not saw
and yet we lost tens of millions of
jobs, would we be happy with that? If
our kids became addicted to AI agents,
would we be happy with that? And I think
once again I want to get back to the
point that some of the founders of this
industry,
people who know more about it than
anybody else in the world are telling us
that within a few years it is likely
that AI will be smarter than human
beings. That human beings may lose
control
over AI with possibly catastrophic
impacts. How do you ignore those issues?
You tell me. and you ask me a question
about what are the Democrats doing. We
need a sense of urgency right now to
address these issues. Clearly, that is
not the case. All right, with that,
thank you all very much.
>> Thank you.