to every aspect of our society.
Artificial intelligence and robotics
will impact our economy,
our political lives, our privacy, our
emotional well-being, our environment,
and even our survival.
The survival of humanity on this planet.
The scale, scope, and speed of this
change will be unprecedented.
That is not the view of Bernie Sanders.
That is the view of some of the most
knowledgeable people in the world who
have developed AI, who study AI.
According to Demis Husabis,
the head of Google's deep mind, the head
of Google's deep mind,
the AI revolution will be 10 times
bigger than the industrial revolution
and 10 times faster.
In other words, the AI revolution
will have 100 times the impact that the
industrial revolution had. People left
the farms, they went to work in
factories. People left factories, they
went to work in offices. According to
the head of Google's deep mind, this
revolution will be 100 times more
impactful.
And Mr. President,
it's not just what the leaders of the AI
companies are saying.
Take a look at what they are doing.
This year, four four AI companies are
spending almost 700
billion dollars to build out data
centers across this country. as a
percentage of G GDP that is 10 times
greater than what we spent each year on
the moon landing going to the moon.
Despite the extraordinary importance of
this issue and the speed at which it is
progressing
AI has gotten far too little discussion
here in Congress.
I fear very much that while the American
people are deeply concerned about the
economic, the spiritual, the political
impact of AI.
Congress is totally unprepared to
respond to the existential changes that
are taking place. We are way, way, way
behind where the American people are in
terms of their concerns.
Here are, in my view, a few questions,
just a few, that members of Congress and
the American people should be asking.
Question number one, a rather obvious
question. Who is pushing the AI and
robotics revolution? ordinary people
going up and saying, "Hey, we got to
automate factories. We got to do this.
We got to do." Who's pushing it? Well, I
think we all know what the answer is.
The answer is Mr. Musk, Mr. Bezos,
Mr. Zuckerberg, Mr. Ellison. These are
some of the wealthiest people in the
world, and they are investing hundreds
of billions of dollars in AI and
robotics.
Okay, fair enough. Why are they doing
it?
Why are these multi-billionaires
investing huge sums of money into these
new technologies?
Do you think it's because they are
staying up nights and they are saying,
"My goodness, 60% of the American people
are struggling economically. They're
living paycheck to paycheck. Can't
afford groceries. They can't afford
housing. They can't afford health care.
And that is why we are going to push
these technologies to improve life for
ordinary Americans.
Well, maybe,
but I doubt that very much. I think the
answer is obvious. These
multi-billionaires
are investing in AI and robotics
because those investments will increase
their wealth and power exponentially.
They will make massive profits.
In other words, the richest and most
powerful people on earth will become
even richer and more powerful.
And another question
I think that we obviously should be
asking is
what will the impacts of AI and robotics
be on our society? How is it going to
impact us? Pretty obvious question in my
view and according to the people who
have studied this issue extensively
including Nobel Prize winners.
AI and robotics will bring about the
most rapid societal transformation in
human history.
Let me repeat, AI and robotics will
bring about the most rapid societal
transformation in human history. Among
other things, AI and robotics will
transform our economy
with massive job displacement.
It will impact our emotional well-being
and how we relate to each other as human
beings.
It will lead to a massive invasion of
privacy.
It will threaten our democratic
institutions
and will bring severe harm to our
environment.
Further and frighteningly,
some very knowledgeable people fear that
what was once seen as science fiction
could soon become a reality.
and that is that super intelligent AI
could become smarter than humans, could
become independent of human control, and
pose an existential threat to the human
race.
In other words, this is what they used
to make science fiction movies about.
But some of the most knowledgeable
people on earth, including people who
have helped develop this technology
actually believe human beings could lose
control over the planet to artificial
intelligence.
Question number four,
what happens to working people, to
ordinary Americans
during this revolutionary upheaval?
Well, don't take my word for it. I'm not
an expert on it. Let's hear what the
leaders in the industry are saying in
their own words. Not Bernie Sanders.
This is what the people who have
invested hundreds of billions of dollars
in the industry are saying.
Elon Musk,
who has made massive investments in AI
and robotics, recently said, quote, "AI
and robots will replace all jobs." End
quote. Now, is Mr. Mus exaggerating? Is
he wrong? I don't know. But I think you
might want to take a listen to one of
the most powerful people on earth who is
investing very heavily in these
technologies.
Bill Gates, another multi-billionaire
investing heavily in AI.
Uh he predicted that humans quote won't
be needed for most things end quote.
Mustafa Sullyman, the CEO of Microsoft
AI AI, the CEO of Microsoft AI said most
white collar work quote will be fully
automated by an AI within the next 12 to
18 months
end quote. Not 12 to 18 years, 12 to 18
months. That is the CEO of Microsoft AI.
Somebody might be a little bit concerned
about that here in Congress.
Last week, the Wall Street Journal
reported that Jeff Bezos, the fourth
richest man alive, who's worth over $200
billion,
is seeking to raise
$100 billion to purchase factories all
over America. Okay. One of the richest
guys in the world is seeking to raise a
hundred billion dollars to purchase
factories all over the country. His goal
replace the millions of workers who are
employed in these plants with robots.
Maybe somebody here might be raising
some concerns about the fact that we are
on the beginning of the end of
manufacturing jobs in the United States.
And from Mr. Bezos, this is not just an
idle threat.
According to the New York Times, Mr.
Bezos plans to fully automate Amazon
operations. He owns Amazon. So he wants
to fully automate Amazon operations
beginning by replacing at least 600,000
workers with robots. So this is a guy
who has a track record. That is what he
is doing right now. And he wants to
expand that vision all across the
country. Basically wipe out
manufacturing jobs in America and get
rid of millions of workers.
Why does he want to do it? Well, the
answer is fairly obvious
because AI and robots will cost
employers far less than human labor.
Robots work 24 hours a day, seven days a
week.
Robots do not need sick days or health
care. They don't take Christmas or New
Year's Day off.
They will end up costing employers a
fraction of what human labor costs.
As Dario Amodai, the head of Anthropic,
has said, "AI quote, isn't a substitute
for specific human jobs,
but rather a general labor substitute
for humans end quote."
And according to Open AI's charter, its
charter, its mission is to build quote,
highly autonomous systems that
outperform humans at most economically
valuable work. End of quote. In other
words, what these guys are working
toward is creating an AI which can do
virtually any job better than a human
being can do.
What are the impacts of that? Well, you
know, we might want to have a discussion
about that here in the Congress. As the
ranking member of the US Senate Health,
Education, Labor, and Pensions
Committee, I released a number of months
ago a wellressearched report finding
that AI, automation, and robotics could
replace nearly 100 million jobs in
America over the next decade. 100
million jobs, including 47% of truck
drivers, 64% of accountants, and 89% of
fast food workers, among many other
occupations.
There are towns and cities in America.
We're already seeing a lot of driverless
vehicles in Texas. Now, you have 18
wheelers going down the road and
nobody's driving those trucks. and
everything being equal. That will be the
future unless we begin to start talking
about it and figure out how we make AI
and robotics work for workers, not just
the richest people on Earth.
We are already, not next year, not 10
years from now, we are already starting
to see the impact of AI on the working
class of this country.
Researchers at Stanford released a paper
in November called Canaries in the Coal
Mine that found that there has already
been a 16% relative decline in
employment for younger workers in jobs
exposed to AI like computer programming
and customer service. Further, 42% of
new college graduates are undermployed.
At the same time, for every new job
posting, there are now on average 242
job applicants. In other words, for our
young people,
getting a job is going to be
increasingly difficult.
If open AI is successful in building
quote what they want to build highly
autonomous systems that outperforms
humans at most economically valuable
work end quote. I have a very simple
question that we might be discussing
here on the floor of the Senate.
What happens to those workers?
How will they be able to find new jobs
if there are no jobs to find?
How are they going to feed their
families? How are they going to buy
health care?
How are they going to stay alive?
If AI and robotics eliminate millions of
jobs and create massive unemployment,
how will people survive if they have no
income?
How do government programs like Social
Security and Medicare survive if workers
are not paying taxes?
And when you don't work, you don't pay
taxes.
Another question that we must be
discussing.
What impact will AI have on our ability
to relate to each other as human beings?
What impact will it have on our
emotional well-being?
Well, work is one of the ways that we
connect to each other. In many cases,
work also gives our lives meaning and
purpose. We all, whether we are doctors
or janitors, scientists or snowplow
operators, want to serve our communities
and be productive members of society. We
want to give back. And what happens when
millions of people lose their jobs,
their meaning and purpose, and their
source of connection to each other?
I am also concerned, and it's not just
me. Parents all over this country are
deeply concerned about the impact that
AI is having on the emotional well-being
of our kids and in fact all people.
According to a recent poll by Common
Sense Media, 72%
of American teenagers say they have used
AI for companionship
and more than half do so regularly.
So, let's take a deep breath and ask
ourselves a simple question.
What does it mean for our young people
to form friendships to become
emotionally dependent
on AI
while at the same time they become
increasingly isolated from other human
beings?
Does anyone in America think that the
past 20 years of social media have been
good and healthy for children's mental
health and cognitive capabilities?
I suspect most people understand that is
not the case. The statistics are quite
clear.
Mental health among young people is in
crisis. According to the US Health and
Human Services Department, one in five
pe young people have a diagnosed mental
health condition such as anxiety or
depression. From 2016 to 2023, the
prevalence of anxiety has increased by
over 60%.
Further and very importantly,
studies indicate that there has been a
cognitive decline
in young people in our country and in
fact in countries all over the world. In
America today, more students are reading
below a basic level than 20 years ago.
It appears that the more time kids spend
on screens,
the worse it is for their brains.
Does anyone really think we should now
entrust the same big tech companies that
have gotten our kids hooked on screens
and social media with even more power
over our children's well-being and
development?
That's a question that we need to be
discussing long and hard
question. Another question that I think
we should be asking.
Will AI result in a massive invasion
of our privacy and our civil liberties?
For decades,
companies have been collecting our
personal information.
what we search for online, where we
visit, who we talk to, what we purchase.
Now, AI makes it possible for someone to
quickly analyze all of that disperate
information,
find patterns, and create profiles of
us.
Larry Ellison, the second wealthiest
person on earth and a major investor in
AI,
predicts an AI powered surveillance
state is coming where quote, "Citizens
will be on their best behavior because
we are constantly recording and
reporting everything that is going on."
End of quote for Mr. Ellison.
Last week in my office,
I had an extremely interesting
experience.
I spoke with Anthropics AI Claude about
the privacy risks posed by AI.
And here is what Claude told me. This is
a quote from Claude.
When companies and governments have
detailed profiles of millions of people,
they have power over those people in
ways most Americans don't fully grasp.
They can manipulate your choices,
predict your behavior, and influence
your thinking." End of quote. That's
from Claude. I don't know if you're
supposed to quote AI, but that is what
AI said. In other words, with AI, we
will reach the stage where every phone
call, every email, every text, every
bank and medical record could be
analyzed in a matter of minutes.
Do we trust companies that have made
billions of dollars in selling our
information with extraord this
extraordinary power to instantly know
everything about us?
My fear is that if we allow the current
situation to continue, privacy
as a human right will disappear. Another
question that needs to be seriously
discussed.
What impact will AI have on our
democracy? We're already facing enormous
threats
from campaign finance, a corrupt
campaign finance system, etc. What
impact will AI have on our democracy?
AI will mean that images, statements,
and videos you see from public officials
and candidates may be totally false.
In other words, words can be put into
the mouths of individuals in a way that
it is virtually impossible to detect.
Let me give you one rather personal
example.
Here is an image of a guy named Bernie
Sanders, senator from Vermont.
And in this image or on this video,
Senator Bernie Sanders is promoting a
website that provides a government
rebate.
Just one problem.
I never said the words that they have
coming out of my mouth.
There is no government rebate. This
whole thing is a total scam. Well, I
must say the picture is not all that
bad.
But
this is something that we're going to
see more and more of.
And this is obviously not something
that's just done to me. These so-called
deep fakes
have been created uh of many well-known
people. So sometimes you're seeing
people who you know saying things sounds
a little weird. Why are they saying
that? Well, you know what? They are not
saying that. It's a fake.
And I want you to appreciate that. If
two days before an election or candidate
gets up there and says all these wild
and crazy things, you say, "Wow, why is
that guy saying that?" Well, you know
what? He or she may not be saying that.
It may be a total fake. The line between
reality,
what is true,
and misinformation, the distortion of
truth, is increasingly being blurred.
We're seeing that every day on the
internet.
Mr. President, if we cannot distinguish,
Madame President, if we cannot
distinguish between reality and
misinformation,
what will in fact happen to our
democratic institutions?
An issue I think we need to be thinking
about.
Further, what impact is AI having on our
environment?
AI requires zillions of calculations.
Those calculations require huge data
centers which in turn require a massive
amount of electricity and water. For
example, Meta is building a data center
in Louisiana the size of Manhattan
that will use as much electricity as 1.6
million homes.
One data center will use as much
electricity as 1.6 million homes. The
increased demand for electricity is
leading to higher electric rates. Over
the past 5 years, wholesale electricity
costs have increased by up to 200 in six
267%
in areas near data centers.
Further, this increased demand will
drive a massive expansion of fossil
fuels when we are already seeing the
devastating impacts of the global crisis
of climate change.
Further question,
does AI pose an existential risk to our
planet and to the survival of humanity?
rather a fundamental
question that I think we might want to
be discussing. So let me pose it again.
Does AI pose an existential risk to our
planet and to the survival of humanity?
This guy is named Dr. Jeffrey Hitten. He
is considered by most people to be the
godfather of AI. He did the
groundbreaking work which led us to
where we are today. Received a Nobel
Prize in physics a few years ago
and what Dr. Hinton says 10 to 20%
chance
they wipe us out.
AI. Many of the most knowledgeable
people on this issue believe that AI
will become smarter than humans. It's
not a question of whether that will
happen. It's a question of when that
will happen.
AI has already developed concerning
patterns.
AI today can lie, it can cheat, and it
can blackmail. In other words, we
already are beginning to lose control of
AI. Now, what happens when AI becomes
smarter than we are?
This concerns, this concern about super
intelligence is why leading experts like
the godfather of AI, Dr. Jeffrey Hinton,
have warned there is a real chance that
AI could wipe out humanity. I don't want
to get people too nervous, but that is
what some people are saying.
There are a number, it's not just him,
there are number of leading people. I
was in California last month talking to
a number of people in the industry. And
the idea that humans can lose control of
AI, that AI can act independently and
cause extraordinary damage to the human
race is not just science fiction. It's
what many of these guys believe.
That leads to my final set of questions.
Where is the Congress?
Now, it's hard not to imagine that these
issues that we're talking about are of
enormous consequence to every man,
woman, and child in this country.
And this is not new news. Poll after
poll shows the American people are
deeply concerned about the economic
impacts impacts on their kids, the
existential threats, etc. So where is
Congress? What exactly has the House and
the Senate done so far to address the
extraordinary challenges posed by
artificial intelligence?
The answer,
not much. Well, why has Congress been
totally ineffective on this issue? And
the answer will not surprise the
American people. We have a corrupt
campaign finances system.
And too often members of Congress are
worried about their campaign
contributions rather than the needs of
their constituents.
The AI oligarchs, some of the wealthiest
people in the country, running
enormously profitable and well-funded
companies, have already spent over $150
million buying influence.
$150 million telling Congress, "Leave us
alone. We got it. Don't get involved in
these issues. We will determine, we the
wealthiest people on earth, will
determine the future of humanity.
Meanwhile, last week, the Trump
administration
put out a comprehensive legislative
framework on AI that is all four pages
long, not quite so comprehensive. In the
midst of a massive and unprecedented
attack on the working class of this
country, the Trump administration
solution says, quote, "Congress should
not create any new federal rulemaking
body to regulate AI." End of quote.
Leave the multi-billionaires running the
industry alone. They make a lot of
campaign contributions. The rich are
getting richer. Leave them alone.
In the midst of a massive and
unprecedented attack on our humanity,
the Trump administration solution says,
quote, "States should not be permitted
to regulate AI development." End quote.
In other words, instead of the United
States Congress representing the
interests of ordinary Americans, the
Trump administration and many members of
Congress in both parties, by the way,
want to allow a handful of billionaires
to race forward to develop AI for
increased power and wealth for
themselves. That is the bad news and
it's pretty scary news. Now, here is the
good news. The American people, despite
the inactivity of Congress, the American
people are fighting back. In community
after community, Americans are
organizing against data centers that are
powering the AI revolution. And they are
winning, taking on very powerful
corporations. And many of these
communities are deeply red,
conservative, some are progressive.
Ordinary people looking around them and
saying, "You know what? We don't think
these data centers are going to do our
community any good. They're going to
raise our rates, put pressure on our
water, destroy the local environment. We
don't want them.
More than, in fact, more than 100 local
communities around the country have
enacted moratoriums on data centers and
12 states are pushing forward with
statewide moratorum proposals.
And here's an important point that I
think has not gotten anywhere near the
discussion that it deserves.
Three years ago, in March of 2023,
more than a thousand leading AI experts,
including Elon Musk, Yosua Benjio, and
Stuart Russell, and many, many others,
these are leaders in the industry,
called for AI labs to quote, immediately
pause for at least six months end quote.
and if such a pause were not enacted
called on governments to quote step in
and institute a moratorum end of quote.
They recognized that quote advanced AI
could represent a profound change in the
history of life on Earth
and should be planned for and managed
with commensurate care and resources and
of quote.
And then these experts again these are
some of the most knowledgeable people on
AI in the world. They asked a series of
questions. Quote, "Should we let
machines flood our information channels
with propaganda and untruth? Should we
automate away all the jobs, including
the fulfilling ones? Should we develop
nonhuman minds that might eventually
outnumber, outsmart, obsolete, and
replace us? Should we risk loss of
control of our civilization?"
End quote. These are some of the leading
and most knowledgeable people in the AI
industry. Three years ago, they
concluded, quote, such decisions must
not be delegated to unelected tech
leaders. Powerful AI systems should be
developed only once we are confident
that their effects will be positive and
their risks will be manageable. end of
quote. And Madame President, I agree
with what these scientists and industry
leaders said. We need to slow down the
development of AI
to give democracy, to give ordinary
people a chance to catch up.
Unfortunately, several years have come
and gone since this letter has come out
and there has been no pause and there
has been no action of significance on
the part of Congress. And that is why I
will be introducing legislation tomorrow
to ban the development of new AI data
centers. A moratorum will give us the
chance to figure out how to make sure
that AI benefits the working families of
this country, not just a handful of
billionaires who want more and more
wealth and more and more power. A
moratorum will give us the time to
figure out how to ensure that AI is safe
and effective and prevent the worst
outcomes. A moratorum will give us the
time to figure out how to make sure AI
does not harm our environment or jack up
the electric bills that we pay. Bottom
line, a moratorum will give the American
people the time to determine how we can
make AI and robotics work for them,
not just a few very wealthy people.
We need to pass this moratorum here. We
need to slow down the development of AI
around the world and we need to bring
the international community together to
address the risk posed by AI.
And I can tell you that
in China, in Europe, in countries all
over the world,
there is deep concern about the safety
of AI and the possible loss of human
control over AI. So, Madame President,
we are looking at the most sweeping and
impactful
technological revolution in the history
of humanity. It will impact all of us in
so many ways. The Congress remains too
busy raising campaign contributions from
the industry rather than standing up for
the needs of working people. That has
got to change and I look forward to
working with my colleagues to make
certain that we finally pass a
moratorum, slow this down and make AI
and robotics work for all of us, not
just a few. Madam President, thank you.
I yield the floor.