Thanks very much for joining me. I will
soon be introducing legislation calling
for a moratorum on the construction of
new data centers. Now, as a result, I've
been called a lite, anti-inovation,
anti-progress, pro-Chinese, among many
other things. So, why am I doing that?
Why am I calling for a moratorum on the
construction of new data centers? Bottom
line,
we are at the beginning of the most
profound technological revolution in
world history. That's the truth. This is
a revolution which will bring
unimaginable changes to our world. This
is a revolution which will impact our
economy with massive job displacement.
It will threaten our democratic
institutions. It will impact our
emotional well-being and what it even
means to be a human being. It will
impact how we educate and raise our
kids. It will impact the nature of
warfare, something we are seeing uh
right now in Iran. Further and
frighteningly, some very knowledgeable
people fear that that what was once seen
as science fiction could soon become a
reality. And that is that super
intelligent I AI could become smarter
than human beings could become
independent of human control and pose an
existential threat to the entire human
race. In other words, human beings could
actually lose control over the planet.
And in the midst of all of that, all of
this transformative change, what I have
to tell you is that the United States
Congress hasn't a clue, not a clue, as
to how to respond to these revolutionary
technologies and protect the American
people. And it's not only not having a
clue, they're out busy raising money all
day long from AI and their super PACs,
which is a whole other problem.
As many of you know, the AI revolution
is being pushed by the wealthiest people
in our country, including Elon Musk,
Jeff Bezos, Larry Ellison, Mark
Zuckerberg, Peter Thiel, and others. All
of these people are multi-billionaires
who, if they are successful at AI, will
become even richer and more powerful
than they are today.
What I want to do now is not tell you my
fears regarding AI and robotics. I want
you to actually hear from them, the
billionaires who are pushing these
technologies. Listen carefully to what
they are saying. Elon Musk, wealthiest
person alive, stated that quote, "AI and
robots will replace all jobs."
All jobs. Working will be optional. End
of quote.
Dario Amodai, the CEO of Anthropic,
predicted that quote, "AI could displace
half of all entrylevel white collar jobs
in the next 1 to five years." and that
quote, "Humanity is about to be handed
almost unimeaginable power, and it is
deeply unclear whether our social,
political, and technological systems
possess the maturity to wield it." End
quote. That's a modi. According to Demis
Hassabas, the head of Google's deep
mind, this is Google's deep mind, the AI
revolution will be 10 times bigger than
the industrial revolution and 10 times
faster. All right, you got that? That
means it will have a 100 times greater
impact on society than the industrial
revolution had. Jeff Bezos, the fourth
richest person in the world, has been
pushing his staff for years to think big
and envision what it would take for
Amazon, which he owns, to fully automate
its operations and replace at least
600,000
warehouse workers with robots. 600,000
jobs gone. Robots doing the work. Bill
Gates, also one of the wealthiest people
on Earth, predicted that humans, quote,
won't be needed for most things, end
quote, such as manufacturing products,
delivering packages, or growing food
over the next decade due to artificial
intelligence.
Mustafa Sullyman the CEO of Microsoft AI
said most white collar work quote will
be fully automated by an AI when the ne
within the next 12 to 18 months end
quote. Jim Fley the CEO of Ford
predicted that AI will eliminate quote
nearly half literally half of all white
collar jobs in the US end quote within
the next decade. I want you to hear this
one. Larry Ellison, also one of the
richest people on Earth and a major
investor in AI, said that there will be
an artificial intelligencepowered
surveillance state where, quote,
citizens will be on their best behavior
because we're constantly recording and
reporting everything that is going on.
End quote. Dr. Jeffrey Hinton,
considered to be the godfather of AI,
believes there is a quote 10% to 20%
chance for AI to wipe us out. End quote.
Mark Zuckerberg, the fifth richest
person in the world, is building a data
center in the state of Louisiana.
A data center that is the size of
Manhattan
and will use three times the quantity of
electricity that the entire city of New
Orleans uses every year.
All right. Now, for many years now,
leading experts have called for
regulation and reasonable pauses to the
development of artificial intelligence
to ensure the safety, the very safety of
humanity. Let's go back to our good
friend Elon Musk. He said back in 2018,
quote, this is Elon Musk. Mark my words,
AI is far more dangerous than nukes.
So why do we have no regulatory
oversight? This is insane. End quote
Elon Musk.
In March of 2023,
over 1,000 business leaders in the big
tech industry, prominent scientists, AI
researchers, and academics co-signed an
open letter entitled, quote, "Pause
giant AI experiments" end quote,
stating, "We must ask ourselves,
should we let machines flood our
information channels with propaganda?
and untruth.
Should we automate away all the jobs,
including the fulfilling ones? Should we
develop nonhuman minds that might
eventually outnumber, outsmart,
obsolete, and replace us? Should we risk
control, loss of control of our
civilization?
Should we risk loss of control of our
civilization? Such decisions must not be
delegated to unelected tech leaders.
Therefore, we call on all AI labs to
immediately pause for at least 6 months
the training of AI systems more more
powerful than GPT4.
This pause should be public and
verifiable and include all key actors.
If such a pause cannot be enacted
quickly, governments should step in and
institute a moratorum. End of quote.
That is what
some of the leaders in the AI industry
have said. And clearly where we are
right now is that there has not been any
pause. there has been massive amounts of
competition between one company and the
other between the United States and
China. So bottom line is that in my view
to protect our workers from losing their
jobs to protect human beings from
attacks on their mental health to
protect our kids
to protect the safety of human life.
Yeah, we need a moratorium on data
centers. We need to take a deep breath.
We need to make sure that AI and
robotics work for all of us, not just a
handful of billionaires. Thanks very
much.